<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
          "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [

  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros-en.ent" >
  <!ENTITY bibliography SYSTEM "../stylesheets/bibliography-en.xml">
  <!ENTITY changelog SYSTEM "changelog-2.0.xml">

  %entities;
]>
<book lang="en" id="releasenotes-ucc-2.0-en">
    <bookinfo>
      <title>UCC 2.0 release notes</title>
      <subtitle>Release notes for the installation and update of Univention Corporate Client (UCC) 2.0</subtitle>

        <revhistory>
            <revision>
                <revnumber>2.0</revnumber>
                <date>30 Apr 2014</date>
            </revision>
        </revhistory>

		<legalnotice>
		  <para>
			Alle Rechte vorbehalten. / All rights reserved.
		  </para>

		  <para>
			(c) 2012 bis 2014 Univention GmbH
		  </para>

		  <para>
			Mary-Somerville-Straße 1, 28359 Bremen, Deutschland/Germany
		  </para>

		  <para>
			feedback@univention.de
		  </para>

		  <para>
			Jede aufgeführte Marke und jedes Warenzeichen steht im Eigentum
			ihrer jeweiligen eingetragenen Rechtsinhaber. Linux ist ein
			eingetragenes Warenzeichen von Linus Torvalds.
		  </para>

		  <para>
			The mentioned brand names and registered trademarks are owned by
			the respective legal owners in each case. Linux is a registered
			trademark of Linus Torvalds.
		  </para>
		</legalnotice>

    </bookinfo>

    <chapter id="relnotes:highlights">
	  <title>Release highlights</title>

		<para>
		  With Univention Corporate Client 2.0 the first major release update of Univention Corporate
		  Client (UCC) is now available. It provides several improvements and bugfixes:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem><para>
			The underlying Ubuntu base has been updated to Kubuntu 14.04. Consequently, a great deal
			of software components have been renewed: KDE 4.13, Linux kernel 3.13, Libreoffice
			4.2.3, Xorg 15. All the Univention packages imported from UCS have been updated to the
			version of UCS 3.2-2.
		  </para></listitem>

		  <listitem><para>
			The initial configuration of Univention Corporate Client is now performed via a wizard
			in the &ucsUMC;. This considerably simplifies the initial setup. In addition, the UCC images
			can now be administrated in their own UMC module.
		  </para></listitem>

		  <listitem><para>
			Support for operating xrdp terminal services has been integrated: A KDE Linux desktop is provided via the RDP
			protocol. In addition to access from UCC thin clients, this also allows access from
			Windows or MacOS X computers. The RDP access is very bandwidth efficient.
		  </para></listitem>

		  <listitem><para>
			For licensing reasons, it is not possible to distribute the Citrix Receiver with
			UCC. The installation is now integrated in the &ucsUMC; setup wizard, reducing the installation
			efforts to just a few clicks.
		  </para></listitem>
			
		  <listitem><para>
			A great number of improvements have been made to the UCC image build system, and as such
			the generated images are now smaller in size, among other things. 
		  </para></listitem>

		  <listitem><para>
			UCC now also supports the rollout of systems in the UEFI boot standard.
		  </para></listitem>

		  <listitem><para>
			The operation of UCC systems with an encrypted hard drive has been considerably
			facilitated; the corresponding option can now be configured easily in the &ucsUMC;.
		  </para></listitem>

		  <listitem><para>
			UCC systems can now be configured to avoid PXE boots and start directly from their local
			storage. This reduces the bootup time.
		  </para></listitem>

		  <listitem><para>
			The configuration of UCC systems has been simplified; print servers, CIFS home shares
			and proxy settings can now be centrally configured through policies.
		  </para></listitem>

		  <listitem><para>
			UCC now uses NeutrinoRDP as its standard RDP client. Among other things, this offers
			support for multi-monitor operation.
		  </para></listitem>

		  <listitem><para>
			A whole range of bug fixes and smaller improvements have been integrated. UCC can now
			also be monitored with Nagios, for example.
		  </para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

    </chapter>

    <!-- <chapter id="relnotes:prepare"> -->
	<!--   <title>Preparation of update</title> -->

	<!-- 	<para> -->
	<!-- 	</para> -->

	<!-- 	<para> -->
	<!-- 	</para> -->

	<!-- 	<para> -->
	<!-- 	</para> -->
	<!-- </chapter> -->

    <chapter>
	  <title>Postprocessing of the update</title>
	  <para>
		UCS installations, in which the &ucsMaster; was installed in a release older than 2.3 still
		use MD5 as the hashing algorithm for the SSL certificates. Later releases use SHA1 as the
		hashing algorithm. UCC clients cannot join a domain still using MD5 hashes. The necessary
		steps to migrate a UCS domain from MD5 to SHA1 are documented in the Univention Support
		Database (<ulink url="http://sdb.univention.de/1150"/>).
	  </para>
	</chapter>

    <chapter>
	  <title>Notes on selected packages</title>

	  <section>
		<title>User switches using <command>su</command></title>
		<para>
		  Switching from one non-root user account to another non-root user account with the
		  <command>su</command> command doesn't work. Switching to the root account is not affected.
		  The underlying bug cannot be easily fixed as it would lead to invasive changes. As a
		  workaround it is possible to first switch to root and then switch to the user account, e.g.

		  <programlisting>
$ su root
$ su testuser
		  </programlisting>

		  More information can be found at <ulink url="&ucsBug;30243">Bug 30243</ulink>.
		</para>
	  </section>

	  <section>
	  	<title>Terminal services based on X11 forwarding</title>
	  	<para>
		  Terminal services based on X11 forwarding are no longer supported. The corresponding
		  &ucsUMC; policy still exists, but is now only used by UCC 1.0 systems. This policy will be
		  removed in a subsequent UCC version.
	  	</para>
	  </section>

	  <section>
	  	<title>RDP logins and PAM home mounts after a password change at LightDM</title>
	  	<para>
		  If the user password is changed during the login at the LightDM Login Manager (e.g.,
		  because the <guimenu>Change password on next login</guimenu> user option is activated or
		  because a password has expired), the password change is effected via Kerberos. This
		  Kerberos password change is not "visible" for PAM modules executed after authentication. 
		  The RDP session script and the PAM module for mounting the home directory via CIFS,
		  however, access the cached password and, as a result, the login fails the first time. The
		  correct password is then available for the second login attempt.
	  	</para>
	  </section>

	</chapter>

    <chapter>
	  <title>Changelog</title>
	  <para>
		Listed are the changes since UCC 1.0:
	  </para>

	  &changelog;

	</chapter>

    <?dbhtml-include href="../stylesheets/piwiki.html"?>
</book>
