<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
	<!ENTITY % extensions SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros.ent" >
	<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros-en.ent" >
	%extensions;
	%entities;
]>
<book lang="en" id="releasenotes-ucc-2.1-en">
    <bookinfo>
      <title>UCC 2.1 release notes</title>
      <subtitle>Release notes for the installation and update of Univention Corporate Client (UCC) 2.1</subtitle>

        <revhistory>
            <revision>
                <revnumber>2.1</revnumber>
                <date>22 July 2015</date>
            </revision>
        </revhistory>

		<legalnotice lang="">
		  <para>
			Alle Rechte vorbehalten. / All rights reserved.
		  </para>

		  <para>
			(c) 2012 bis 2015 Univention GmbH
		  </para>

		  <para>
			Mary-Somerville-Straße 1, 28359 Bremen, Deutschland/Germany
		  </para>

		  <para>
			<email>feedback@univention.de</email>
		  </para>

		  <para lang="de">
			Jede aufgeführte Marke und jedes Warenzeichen steht im Eigentum
			ihrer jeweiligen eingetragenen Rechtsinhaber. Linux ist ein
			eingetragenes Warenzeichen von Linus Torvalds.
		  </para>

		  <para lang="en">
			The mentioned brand names and registered trademarks are owned by
			the respective legal owners in each case. Linux is a registered
			trademark of Linus Torvalds.
		  </para>
		</legalnotice>
    </bookinfo>

    <chapter id="relnotes:highlights">
	  <title>Release highlights</title>

		<para>
		  With Univention Corporate Client (UCC) 2.1 the first minor release update of UCC is now available.
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem><para>
			UCC is now Citrix Ready certified.
			This allows Univention to provide the Citrix Receiver with UCC thin client images.
			Citrix Receiver is responsible for the connection to Citrix environments from a thin client operated with UCC.
			The UCC setup wizard still allows the manual installation of specific Citrix Receiver versions.
		  </para></listitem>

		  <listitem><para>
			Support for UCC Image site servers has been added.
			UCC computer objects can now be configured to use a specific server to download UCC Images from.
		  </para></listitem>

		  <listitem><para>
			UCC 2.1 images use the newer Linux kernel and Xorg X11 server version from Kubuntu <wordasword>Utopic</wordasword> by default.
			UCC 2.1 is based on Kubuntu 14.04 and will receive its software and security updates.
		  </para></listitem>

		</itemizedlist>
    </chapter>

    <!-- <chapter id="relnotes:prepare"> -->
	<!--   <title>Preparation of update</title> -->

	<!-- 	<para> -->
	<!-- 	</para> -->

	<!-- 	<para> -->
	<!-- 	</para> -->

	<!-- 	<para> -->
	<!-- 	</para> -->
	<!-- </chapter> -->

    <chapter id="relnotes:postprocessing">
	  <title>Postprocessing of the installation</title>
	  <para>
		UCS installations, in which the &ucsMaster; was installed in a release older than 2.3 still
		use MD5 as the hashing algorithm for the SSL certificates. Later releases use SHA-1 as the
		hashing algorithm. UCC clients cannot join a domain still using MD5 hashes. The necessary
		steps to migrate a UCS domain from MD5 to SHA-1 are documented in the Univention Support
		Database (<u:sdb>1150</u:sdb>).
	  </para>
	</chapter>

    <chapter id="relnotes:packages">
	  <title>Notes on selected packages</title>
	  <section id="relnotes:packages:xrdp">
		  <title>Announcing discontinuation of XRDP terminal services for UCC 3</title>
		  <para>
			With the release of Univention Corporate Client 2.1 Univention announces the discontinuation of XRDP terminal services on UCC for the next major release UCC 3.0.
			This does not affect functionality and support for XRDP UCC terminal services on UCC 2.
		  </para>
	  </section>
	  <section id="relnotes:packages:su">
		<title>User switches using <command>su</command></title>
		<para>
		  Switching from one non-root user account to another non-root user account with the
		  <command>su</command> command doesn't work. Switching to the root account is not affected.
		  The underlying bug cannot be easily fixed as it would lead to invasive changes. As a
		  workaround it is possible to first switch to root and then switch to the user account, e.g.

		  <programlisting lang="sh">
$ su root
$ su testuser
		  </programlisting>

		  More information can be found at <ulink url="&ucsbug;30243">Bug 30243</ulink>.
		</para>
	  </section>

	  <section id="relnotes:packages:pam">
	  	<title>RDP logins and PAM home mounts after a password change at LightDM</title>
	  	<para>
		  If the user password is changed during the login at the LightDM Login Manager (e.g.,
		  because the <guimenu>Change password on next login</guimenu> user option is activated or
		  because a password has expired), the password change is effected via Kerberos. This
		  Kerberos password change is not "visible" for PAM modules executed after authentication. 
		  The RDP session script and the PAM module for mounting the home directory via CIFS,
		  however, access the cached password and, as a result, the login fails the first time. The
		  correct password is then available for the second login attempt.
	  	</para>
	  </section>

	</chapter>

    <chapter id="relnotes:changelog">
	  <title>Changelog</title>
	  <para>
		Listed are the changes since UCC 2.0:
	  </para>

	  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="changelog-2.1.xml" xpointer="xpointer(/chapter/section)"/>
	</chapter>

	<!--
	<bibliography id="bibliography">
		<bibliomixed id="ext-doc-inst"/>
	</bibliography>
	-->

    <?dbhtml-include href="../stylesheets/piwiki.html"?>
</book>
