<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
	<!ENTITY % extensions SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros.ent" >
	<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros-en.ent" >
	%extensions;
	%entities;
]>
<book lang="en" id="releasenotes-ucc-3.0-en">
    <bookinfo>
      <title>UCC 3.0 release notes</title>
      <subtitle>Release notes for the installation and update of Univention Corporate Client (UCC) 3.0</subtitle>

		<legalnotice lang="">
		  <para>
			Alle Rechte vorbehalten. / All rights reserved.
		  </para>

		  <para>
			(c) 2012 bis 2016 Univention GmbH
		  </para>

		  <para>
			Mary-Somerville-Straße 1, 28359 Bremen, Deutschland/Germany
		  </para>

		  <para>
			<email>feedback@univention.de</email>
		  </para>

		  <para lang="de">
			Jede aufgeführte Marke und jedes Warenzeichen steht im Eigentum
			ihrer jeweiligen eingetragenen Rechtsinhaber. Linux ist ein
			eingetragenes Warenzeichen von Linus Torvalds.
		  </para>

		  <para lang="en">
			The mentioned brand names and registered trademarks are owned by
			the respective legal owners in each case. Linux is a registered
			trademark of Linus Torvalds.
		  </para>
		</legalnotice>
    </bookinfo>

    <chapter id="relnotes:highlights">
	  <title>Release highlights</title>

		<para>
		  With Univention Corporate Client (UCC) 3.0 the second major release update of Univention Corporate Client is now available. It provides several improvements and bugfixes:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem><para>
			The Ubuntu base has been updated to version 16.04. A large part of available software components are renewed: Unity 7.4, Linux Kernel 4.4, LibreOffice 5.1.4. All Univention packages imported from UCS have been updated to the version of UCS 4.1
		  </para></listitem>
		  <listitem><para>
			The default Desktop is now Unity, which allows us to provide maintenance of 5 years for UCC 3.0.
		  </para></listitem>
		  <listitem><para>
			UCC desktops are now available as 64-Bit images. Thin client images are still available as 32-Bit.
		  </para></listitem>
		  <listitem><para>
			Clients report their currently installed image to the UCS management system. This allows to easily search for clients which use outdated images.
		  </para></listitem>
		  <listitem><para>
			Clients check and update their position in the UCS LDAP. The move of a computer object now does not require a client rejoin.
		  </para></listitem>
		  <listitem><para>
			Images for 32- and 64-Bit architecture images can be build on UCS servers that are using 64-Bit architecture.
		  </para></listitem>
		  <listitem><para>
			Thin clients update their client policies persistently upon booting, which increases robustness in case the LDAP server is not reachable during boot time.
		  </para></listitem>
		  <listitem><para>
			The RDP and Firefox session scripts can be configured to add additional programm parameters, or to execute arbitrary commands, including the possibility to change the program binary.
		  </para></listitem>
		  <listitem><para>
			It is possible to activate the custom start script feature. This offers the possibility to sync scripts and other files from the image server and execute them at boot time.
		  </para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
    </chapter>

	<chapter id="relnotes:prepare">
		<title>Preparation of update</title>
		<para>
			Due to the switch from 32-Bit to 64-Bit architecture in the UCC desktop image, clients are required to boot via PXE for the image update to work.
		</para>
	</chapter>

    <chapter id="relnotes:postprocessing">
	  <title>Postprocessing of the installation</title>
	  <para>
		UCS installations, in which the &ucsMaster; was installed in a release older than 2.3 still
		use MD5 as the hashing algorithm for the SSL certificates. Later releases use SHA-1 as the
		hashing algorithm. UCC clients cannot join a domain still using MD5 hashes. The necessary
		steps to migrate a UCS domain from MD5 to SHA-1 are documented in the Univention Support
		Database (<u:sdb>1150</u:sdb>).
	  </para>
	</chapter>

    <chapter id="relnotes:packages">
	  <title>Notes on selected packages</title>
	  <section id="relnotes:packages:cifshomemount">
		  <title>Removal of CIFS home mount package with UCC 3</title>
		  <para>
			  With the release of Univention Corporate Client 3.0 the package <package>univention-ucc-cifshome-pam-mount</package> has been removed due to stability and performance issues in medium and large environments.
			  The custom start scripts feature can allow administrators to build similar features if they desire.
		  </para>
	  </section>

	  <section id="relnotes:packages:pam">
	  	<title>RDP logins and PAM home mounts after a password change at LightDM</title>
	  	<para>
		  If the user password is changed during the login at the LightDM Login Manager (e.g.,
		  because the <guimenu>Change password on next login</guimenu> user option is activated or
		  because a password has expired), the password change is effected via Kerberos. This
		  Kerberos password change is not "visible" for PAM modules executed after authentication. 
		  The RDP session script and the PAM module for mounting the home directory via CIFS,
		  however, access the cached password and, as a result, the login fails the first time. The
		  correct password is then available for the second login attempt.
	  	</para>
	  </section>

	</chapter>

    <chapter id="relnotes:changelog">
	  <title>Changelog</title>
	  <para>
		Listed are the changes since UCC 2.1:
	  </para>

	  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="changelog-3.0.xml" xpointer="xpointer(/chapter/section)"/>
	</chapter>

	<!--
	<bibliography id="bibliography">
		<bibliomixed id="ext-doc-inst"/>
	</bibliography>
	-->

    <?dbhtml-include href="../stylesheets/piwiki.html"?>
</book>
