<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
          "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [

  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros-en.ent" >
  <!ENTITY bibliography SYSTEM "../stylesheets/bibliography-en.xml">

  %entities;
]>
<book lang="en" id="quickstart-en-3.2">
<bookinfo>
  <title>Univention Corporate Client</title>
  <subtitle>Quickstart Guide for Univention Corporate Client</subtitle>
  <revhistory>
     <revision>
        <revnumber>2.0</revnumber>
        <date>6 Jun 2014</date>
     </revision>
  </revhistory>
</bookinfo>

<chapter id="uccquickstart:intro">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <para>
	Univention Corporate Client (UCC) is a flexible and very economic alternative for the operation
	and administration of PCs, notebooks and thin clients in companies and institutions. The
	software contains a Linux-based desktop environment optimised for business use. In addition, UCC
	serves as a platform for access to remote desktop solutions and virtualized desktops as well as
	browser or terminal server-based applications.
  </para>

  <para>
	The administration is performed using the standard tools of the UCS management system from
	Univention Corporate Server and integrates seamlessly in the administration of existing domain
	resources.
  </para>

  <para>
	This quickstart guide offers an introduction to Univention Corporate Client. Two application
	scenarios for UCC are presented:
	
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><simpara>
		The management of Linux desktop systems (here taking a notebook with a KDE desktop
		environment as an example). 
	  </simpara></listitem>

	  <listitem><simpara>
		Access to Windows Remote Desktop Services via the RDP protocol using a thin client
	  </simpara></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	If you only wish to test one of these scenarios, one of the two steps can also be skipped.
  </para>

  <para>
	UCC also offers the possibility of providing a KDE Linux desktop terminal server remotely via
	the RDP protocol. It is then possible to access it from thin clients, for example. This is
	documented in the UCC manual <biblioref linkend="ucc-manual"/>.
  </para>

  <para>
	Help on Univention Corporate Client is offered in the Univention Forum: <ulink
	url="http://forum.univention.de/"/>.
  </para>

</chapter>

<chapter id="uccquickstart:requirements">
  <title> Requirements</title>

  <para>
	The following systems are required for the quickstart guide: 

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><simpara>
		A UCS system in which UCC is managed (a UCC environment can also be distributed on several
		systems, this example uses a single-server installation). The UCC images will be stored on
		the UCS system, so there should be sufficient disk space available. At least 2 GiB of free
		space are needed for the thin client image and at least 20 GiB for the desktop image. 
	  </simpara></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	To test the access to a Windows terminal server from a thin client: 

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><simpara>
		A Windows terminal server for the thin client to access.
	  </simpara></listitem>

	  <listitem><simpara>
		A thin client. The thin client must have 2 GiB CompactFlash memory. 
	  </simpara></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	To test the operation of a Linux desktop: 

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><simpara>
		A system on which the Linux desktop is installed. The system should be equipped with at
		least 20 GiB of disk space (the operating system installation requires 15 GiB plus
		additional GiBs for the home directory). 
	  </simpara></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
  </para>

  <para>
	Detailed descriptions of UCC can be found on the website <footnote><para><ulink
	url="http://www.univention.com/products/ucc/"/></para></footnote> and in the UCC manual
	<biblioref linkend="ucc-manual"/>.
  </para>

</chapter>

<chapter id="uccquickstart:ucsinstall">
  <title>Installing the UCS system</title>

  <para>
	UCC requires Univention Corporate Server (UCS) 3.2. The installation of Univention Corporate
	Server is described in the quickstart guide for UCS <biblioref linkend="ucs-quickstart"/>.
  </para>

  <para>
	UCC can be installed on all UCS server roles. In this example, the installation is performed on
	a single-server system. Therefore, <emphasis>Domaincontroller master</emphasis> has to be selected as system role. No
	additional component needs to be selected in the software selection. All available errata
	updates should be installed on the UCS system. 
  </para>

  <para>
	Following successful installation, a login is performed on the Univention Management Console
	(reachable under https://server_ip/) as user <emphasis>Administrator</emphasis>. 
  </para>

  <figure id="quickucc-umc">
	<title>Login at the  UMC</title>
	<graphic scalefit="1" width="40%" fileref="illustrations/umclogin-en.png"/>
  </figure>

  <para>
	During the first login at the Univention Management Console a dialogue is displayed which allows
	the activation of the UCS license for the Univention App Center. For this an e-mail address
	needs to be provided to which the activated license key is sent.
  </para>

  <para>
	The license key can be imported in the UMC by clicking on the gear-wheel symbol in the upper
	menu bar. The menu entry <guimenu>Import new license</guimenu> needs to be selected.
  </para>

  <para>
	Now the UMC module <guimenu>App Center</guimenu> needs to be opened. 
  </para>

  <para>
	In the Univention App Center, select the <emphasis>Univention Corporate Client
	2.0</emphasis> application and click on <guimenu>Install</guimenu>. Following that, a new login
	to UMC needs to be done. 
  </para>

  <para>
	Now a user must be created in the user management of the UMC. It is sufficient to perform the
	minimum required settings.
  </para>

</chapter>

<chapter id="uccquickstart:thinclient">
  <title>Configuring thin client access to Windows terminal servers</title>

  <section id="uccquickstart:thinclient:setup">
	<title>Introduction</title>
	
	<para>
	  The <guimenu>UCC setup</guimenu> UMC module must be run. In the first menu item you can select
	  whether desktops and/or thin clients are to be set up. Select <guimenu>Thin client
	  configuration</guimenu> and click <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The UCC systems are installed via images, i.e., the complete operating system is replaced
	  during installations and updates (user data are stored separately). This makes it possible to
	  run an installation in just a few minutes. Univention provides preconfigured images which are
	  continuously maintained. 
	</para>

	<para>
	  The thin client image must now be downloaded from the Univention server. As it is
	  approximately 300 MB in size, the download may take some time. To do so, enable the
	  <guimenu>Download the UCC thin client image</guimenu> option and click on
	  <guimenu>Next</guimenu>. Once the download is complete, the image is unpacked.
	</para>

	<para>
	  UCS uses so-called network objects to manage IP addresses and DNS/DHCP settings for client
	  systems. Network objects define IP address ranges and provide the next free IP address when a
	  new computer is created.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The following dialogue can be used either to define a new network or to use the network object
	  installed during the installation of the &ucsMaster;.
	</para>

	<para>
	  In the following step, the wizard checks whether a standard gateway is configured in the
	  DHCP. If this is not the case, a dialogue appears in which this can be defined.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The next prompt asks which remote desktop services should be accessed. Select <guimenu>RDP
	  services (Windows Remote Desktop Services, XRDP)</guimenu> and click <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
	</para>

	<para>
	  In addition to the RDP access described here, access to Citrix Terminal Services or a website
	  can also be configured. This is documented in the UCC manual: <biblioref
	  linkend="ucc-manual-citrix"/>, <biblioref linkend="ucc-manual-firefox"/>.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The server to be connected to is entered under <guimenu>Host name of RDP server</guimenu>. If
	  this is a Windows server, the <guimenu>Domain name</guimenu> must also be configured.
	</para>

	<para>
	  After clicking on <guimenu>Next</guimenu>, the configured settings are then shown once again. 
	  Clicking <guimenu>Apply configuration</guimenu> applies them. The UCC image is then downloaded 
	  and unpacked and different Univention Configuration Registry policies are preconfigured.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="uccquickstart:thinclient:createhost">
	<title>Adding a thin client</title>

	<para>
	  Now open the computer module in the UMC and click <guimenu>Add</guimenu>. Select
	  <emphasis>computers/ucc-thinclients</emphasis> as the <guimenu>Container</guimenu> (this
	  container is linked to policies which are configured in the UCC wizard) and <emphasis>Host:
	  Univention Corporate Client</emphasis> as the <guimenu>Type</guimenu>. Then click on
	  <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
	</para>

	<para>
	  You can select any <guimenu>Host name</guimenu>. The network configured in the UCC setup
	  wizard is used as the <guimenu>Network</guimenu> and an <guimenu>IP address</guimenu>
	  suggested based on this (however, it is also possible to use a different one). In addition,
	  the <guimenu>MAC address</guimenu> also needs to be configured. Then click on
	  <guimenu>Next</guimenu>. 
	</para>

	<para>
	  Select <emphasis>Installation with repartitioning and image rollout</emphasis> as the
	  <guimenu>Boot variant</guimenu> and the downloaded thin client image
	  (<emphasis>ucc-2.0-thinclient-image.img</emphasis>) as the <guimenu>Image</guimenu>.
	  Then click <guimenu>Create computer</guimenu>. 
	</para>

	<para>
	  The client has to be started now. A PXE start must be selected in the system's BIOS. The image
	  is started via PXE and the harddrive partitioned and installed following confirmation. The
	  domain join to the UCS domain is performed in the scope of the installation. The join is
	  performed with the <emphasis>Administrator</emphasis> account.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The domain join can also be performed completely automated
	  <biblioref linkend="ucc-manual-automaticrollout"/>.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The session <guimenu>RDP</guimenu> must now be selected in the LightDM login manager. A login
	  can now be performed with the user created in the UMC. A connection to the Windows terminal
	  server is created automatically and it is possible to work on the terminal server. 
	</para>
  </section>
</chapter>

<chapter id="uccquickstart:desktop">
  <title>Configuring Linux desktop systems </title>
	
  <section id="uccquickstart:desktop:setup">
	<title>Introduction</title>
	
	<para>
	  The <guimenu>UCC setup</guimenu> UMC module must be opened. In the first menu item you can
	  select whether desktops and/or thin clients are to be set up. Select <guimenu>Linux desktop
	  systems configuration / XRDP terminal server setup</guimenu> and click
	  <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The UCC systems are installed via images, i.e., the complete operating system is replaced
	  during installations and updates (user data are saved separately). This makes it possible to
	  perform an installation in just a few minutes. Univention provides preconfigured images which
	  are continuously maintained. 
	</para>

	<para>
	  The desktop image must now be downloaded from the Univention server. As it is approximately 1
	  GB in size, the download may take some time. To do so, enable the <guimenu>Download the UCC
	  desktop image option</guimenu> and click on <guimenu>Next</guimenu>. Once the download is
	  complete, the desktop image is unpacked. The UCS system should have at least 20 GiB of free
	  disk space.
	</para>

	<para>
	  UCS uses so-called network objects to manage IP addresses and DNS/DHCP settings for client
	  systems. Network objects define IP address ranges and provide the next free IP address when a
	  new computer is added.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The following dialogue can be used either to define a new network or to use the network object
	  installed during the installation of the &ucsMaster;.
	</para>

	<para>
	  In the following step, the wizard checks whether a standard gateway is configured in the DHCP. If
	  this is not the case, a dialogue appears in which this can be defined.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The configured settings are then shown once again. Clicking <guimenu>Apply
	  configuration</guimenu> applies them. The UCC image is then downloaded and unpacked and
	  different Univention Configuration Registry policies are preconfigured. 
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="uccquickstart:desktop:createhost">
	<title>Adding a desktop</title>

	<para>
	  Now open the computers module of the UMC and click <guimenu>Add</guimenu>. Select
	  <emphasis>computers/ucc-desktops</emphasis> as the <guimenu>Container</guimenu> (this
	  container is linked to policies which are configured in the UCC wizard) and <emphasis>Host:
	  Univention Corporate Client</emphasis> as the <guimenu>Type</guimenu>. Then click on
	  <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
	</para>

	<para>
	  You can select any <guimenu>Host name</guimenu>. The network configured in the UCC setup
	  wizard is used as the <guimenu>Network</guimenu> and an <guimenu>IP address</guimenu>
	  suggested based on this (however, it is also possible to use a different one). In addition,
	  the <guimenu>MAC address</guimenu> also needs to be configured. Then click on <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Select <emphasis>Installation with repartitioning and image rollout</emphasis> as the 
	  <guimenu>Boot variant</guimenu> and the downloaded desktop image
	  (<emphasis>ucc-2.0-desktop-image.img</emphasis>) as the <guimenu>Image</guimenu>. Then click
	  <guimenu>Create computer</guimenu>. 
	</para>

	<para>
	  The client has to be started now. A PXE start must be selected in the system's BIOS. The image
	  is started via PXE and the harddrive partitioned and installed following confirmation. The
	  domain join to the UCS domain is performed in the scope of the installation. The join is
	  performed with the Administrator account.
	</para>

	<para>
	  In a productive UCC installation, the domain join can be performed completely automated
	  <biblioref linkend="ucc-manual-automaticrollout"/>.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The session <guimenu>UCC</guimenu> must now be selected in the LightDM login manager. The
	  login can now be performed with the user created in the UMC. The user can then work with a KDE
	  Plasma desktop. 
	</para>

  </section>
</chapter>

  

<bibliography id="relnotes:bibliography">
  <bibliomixed id="ucc-manual"/>
  <bibliomixed id="ucs-quickstart"/>
  <bibliomixed id="ucc-manual-citrix"/>
  <bibliomixed id="ucc-manual-firefox"/>
  <bibliomixed id="ucc-manual-automaticrollout"/>
  <bibliomixed id=""/>


</bibliography>

<?dbhtml-include href="../stylesheets/piwik.html"?>
</book>
