<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
	  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
	<!ENTITY % extensions SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros.ent" >
	<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros-en.ent" >
	%extensions;
	%entities;
]>
<chapter id="desktop:chapter">
  <title>Univention Corporate Client desktop environment</title>

  <section id="desktop:intro">
	<title>Introduction</title>
	<para>
	  Univention Corporate Client offers a desktop environment based on the KDE Plasma desktop in
	  version 4.13. It offers a compilation of software components suitable for typical business
	  applications.
	</para>

	<figure id="ucc-desktop"><title>Univention Corporate Client desktop</title>
	<graphic scalefit="1" width="80%" fileref="illustrations40/ucc-desktop.png"/>
	</figure>
  
	<para>
	  Extensive documentation and manuals for all the KDE components can be found at <ulink
	  url="http://docs.kde.org/"/>.
	</para>

	<para>
	  LibreOffice is a core application of the Univention Corporate Client and offers the full
	  scope of functions of a modern Office suite. In addition to standardised, open formats such as
	  the OpenDocument format it can also be used to open and edit documents created in other
	  office applications such as Microsoft Office. To ensure uncomplicated distribution, documents
	  can also be easily exported in PDF format. Extensive documentation on LibreOffice can be found at
	  <ulink url="http://www.libreoffice.org/get-help/documentation/"/>.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Mozilla Firefox is also supplied for accessing websites. The Adobe
	  Flash plugin is integrated for the playback of Flash animations.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Thin clients only offer a slimmed down desktop environment based on
	  LXDE. LXDE is only provided for simple administrative environments.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="desktop:proxy">
	<title>Configuration of proxy settings for the desktop</title>
	<para>
	  The proxy settings in Firefox and KDE can be centrally configured via &ucsUCR; variables
	  provide by the package <package>univention-ucc-proxy-settings</package> (see <xref
	  linkend="config:ucr"/>). <envar>ucc/proxy/http</envar> configures a specific proxy,
  e.g. <literal>http://192.168.0.100:3128</literal>. Alternatively the URL to a PAC (<phrase>Proxy
	  Auto-Config</phrase>) file can be provided with the variable <envar>ucc/proxy/autoconfig/url</envar>.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Proxy settings configured with the variables above are immutable for the user. In Firefox the
	  respective dialogues are greyed out. In the system settings of KDE changes can be made in the
	  dialogues, but they are discarded when clicking <guimenu>Apply</guimenu>.
	</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
