<chapter id="desktop:chapter">
<title>Univention Corporate Client desktop environment</title>

<section id="desktop:intro">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <para>
	Univention Corporate Client offers a desktop environment based on
	the KDE Plasma desktop in version 4.8. It offers a compilation of
	software components suitable for typical business applications.
  </para>

  <figure><title>Univention Corporate Client desktop</title>
  <graphic scalefit="1" width="80%" fileref="illustrations/ucc-desktop.png"/>
  </figure>
  
  <para>
	Extensive documentation and manuals for all the KDE components can
	be found at <ulink url="http://docs.kde.org/"/>.
  </para>

  <para>
	LibreOffice is the core application of the Univention Corporate
	Client and offers the full scope of functions of a modern Office
	suite. In addition to standardised, open formats such as the
	OpenDocument format, OpenOffice.org can also be used to open and
	edit documents created in other office applications such as
	Microsoft Office. To ensure uncomplicated distribution, documents can
	also be easily exported in PDF format.
  </para>

  <para>
	Extensive documentation on Libreoffice can be found at
	<ulink url="http://www.libreoffice.org/get-help/documentation/"/>.
  </para>

  <para>
	Mozilla Firefox is also supplied for accessing websites. The Adobe
	Flash plugin is integrated for the playback of Flash animations.
  </para>

  <para>
	Thin clients only offer a slimmed down desktop environment based on
	LXDE. LXDE is only provided for simple administrative environments.
  </para>
</section>

<section id="desktop:proxy">
  <title>Configuration of proxy settings for the desktop</title>
  <para>
	The proxy settings in Firefox and KDE can be centrally configured via &ucsUCR; variables provide by the package <emphasis>univention-ucc-proxy-settings</emphasis> (see
	<xref linkend="config:ucr"/>). <envar>ucc/proxy/http</envar> configures a specific proxy, e.g.
	<emphasis>http://192.168.0.100:3128</emphasis>. Alternatively the URL to a PAC (proxy
	auto-config) file can be provided with the variable <envar>ucc/proxy/autoconfig/url</envar>.
  </para>

  <para>
	Proxy settings configured with the variables above are immutable for the user. In Firefox the
	respective dialogues are greyed out. In the system settings of KDE changes can be made in the
	dialogues, but they are discarded when clicking <guimenu>Apply</guimenu>.
  </para>
</section>

</chapter>
