<chapter id="hardware:chapter">
  <title>Hardware configuration of UCC systems</title>

  <section id="hardware:network">
	<title>Network configuration</title>
	<para>
	  The network configuration of UCC clients is generally performed via DHCP. The configuration of
	  MAC and IP addresses, etc., is performed in the UCS management system, see <xref
	  linkend="umc:manageucc"/>.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The network interfaces of a joined UCC client are managed via the Network Manager. Here you
	  can also configure additional connections uch as a VPN/Wifi access or a static IP address.
	</para>

	<para>
	  During the PXE live boot of a UCC system, the primary interface (eth0) is not managed by
	  Network Manager.
	</para>

	<para>
	  While offline operation is supported for images running the desktop image, thin clients
	  require a permanenent network connection.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The wireless regulatory domain is set to <emphasis>00</emphasis> as standard. With some access
	  points, it can be necessary to configure this to the national code using the command
	  <command>iw reg set</command>.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="hardware:usbthin">
	<title>USB mass storage access on thin clients</title>
	<para>
	  The <emphasis>univention-ucc-remote-mount</emphasis> package installed as standard allows
	  access to the USB-CD/DVD drives, hard drives and sticks connected to a UCC thin client. If a
	  USB mass storage device is connected to the client, a local mount is performed via a udev
	  rule. The terminal service solutions then provide this directory through the terminal
	  session. The additional component <command>cdpinger</command> is used for the integration of
	  USB-CDROM/DVDROMs. VFAT, NTFS and ext* file systems are mounted.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The mounting of mass storage devices is disabled on desktop systems (as mass storage devices
	  are automatically mounted in the KDE desktop anyway). If you still wish to enable the function
	  in exceptional cases, this can be done by setting the &ucsUCRV; <envar>ucc/mount</envar> to
	  <emphasis>true</emphasis>.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The local mount points are made available in UCC, Windows terminal server and XenApp terminal
	  server sessions if the option <guimenu>Allow access to local mass storage</guimenu> is
	  activated in the <guimenu>UCC client configuration</guimenu> policy in the UMC computer
	  management.
	</para>

	<para>
	  In the standard setting, data on thin clients are cached for up to a tenth of a second before
	  they are written on the USB medium. The behaviour can be adapted with the &ucsUCR; variables
	  <envar>ucc/sysctl/dirtywritebackcentisecs</envar> and
	  <envar>ucc/sysctl/dirtyexpiredcentisecs</envar>.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Setting the &ucsUCRV; <envar>ucc/mount/sync</envar> to <emphasis>true</emphasis> allows all
	  changes to be written directly. This generally leads to considerable performance losses.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The access to the mounted USB media is described in the corresponding sections on terminal
	  services (see <xref linkend="terminalservices:chapter"/>).
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="hardware:sound">
	<title>Sound support</title>
	<para>
	  The sound output is activated in UCC clients as standard. Sound is also output in terminal
	  sessions:
	  
	  <itemizedlist>
		<listitem><simpara>
		  In RDP sessions to Windows terminal servers and XRDP terminal servers, audio is
		  transported via an RDP channel.
		</simpara></listitem>

		<listitem><simpara>
		  In Citrix XenApp sessions, sound output is transmitted via the Citrix protocol.
		</simpara></listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</para>

	<para>
	  Information of the configuration of the sound output in terminal services can be found in
	  <xref linkend="terminalservices:chapter"/>.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="hardware:kernelmodules">
	<title>Managing drivers/kernel modules</title>
	<para>
	  The drivers to be used are recognised automatically during system start and loaded via the
	  udev device manager. At this point, the necessary device links are also created under
	  <filename>/dev/</filename>. If drivers are not detected, kernel modules to be loaded can be
	  added via the &ucsUCRV; <envar>kernel/modules</envar>. If more than one kernel module is to be
	  loaded, these must be separated by a semicolon. The &ucsUCRV; <envar>kernel/blacklist</envar>
	  can be used to configure a list of one or more kernel modules for which automatic loading
	  should be prevented. Multiple entries must also be separated by a semicolon.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="hardware:dualdisplay">
	<title>Configuration of dual-display setups</title>
	<para>
	  UCC uses the Xorg autodetection for the configuration of the graphics adapter. This
	  automatically determines the suitable driver for the graphics card and the appropriate display
	  parameters.
	</para>

	<figure><title>Configuring dual monitor display</title>
	<graphic scalefit="1" width="60%" fileref="illustrations/ucc-hardware-policy.png"/>
	</figure>
	
	<para>
	  Dual-display setups can be configured using a <guimenu>UCC client configuration</guimenu>
	  computer policy in the UCS management system:
	</para>

	<para>
	  To configure a dual-display setup, at least the position of the primary display relative to
	  the secondary display must be specified in the <guimenu>Position of secondary display relative
	  to the primary</guimenu> field:

	  <itemizedlist>
		<listitem><simpara>Left of primary display</simpara></listitem>
		<listitem><simpara>Right of primary display</simpara></listitem>
		<listitem><simpara>Above primary display</simpara></listitem>
		<listitem><simpara>Below primary display</simpara></listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</para>

	<para>
	  Setting the resolutions via the <guimenu>Resolution of primary display</guimenu> and
	  <guimenu>Resolution of secondary display</guimenu> fields is optional: If they are not set,
	  they are assigned the recommended value (<command>xrandr --auto</command>). The values for
	  width and height should be separated by an <emphasis>x</emphasis>, e.g.,
	  <emphasis>1024x768</emphasis>.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The Xorg-internal names of the displays are also automatically detected and listed
	  alphabetically. In this way, the order is always fixed. If automatic determination of the
	  display names is used, a message like the one below is written in the syslog:

	  <programlisting>
Dec 17 13:12:34 x201 logger: The display settings for x201 were
queried automatically, if you want to set them through a policy
use the display names LVDS1 and VGA1
	  </programlisting>

	  These values can then be specified in the <guimenu>Name of primary display</guimenu> and
	  <guimenu>Name of secondary display</guimenu> fields.
	</para>

	<para>
	  For special cases such as the configuration of a third display, a local display setup script
	  can be configured. This is done by setting the UCR variable &ucsUCRV;
	  <envar>ucc/displayscript</envar> to a script, which is then run for the Xorg configuration
	  instead of the standard script.
	</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
