<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
	  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
	<!ENTITY % extensions SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros.ent" >
	<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros-en.ent" >
	%extensions;
	%entities;
]>
<chapter id="installation:chapter">
<title>Installation</title>
<para>
  Univention Corporate Client integrates into the management system
  of Univention Corporate Server. UCS 4.0 is a prerequisite for the
  installation of UCC.
</para>

<para>
  The UCS integration packages are installed via the Univention App
  Center. General information on the Univention App Center can be found
  in the UCS manual <biblioref linkend="ucs-manual"/>.
</para>

<figure id="app-center"><title>Installing UCC in the Univention App Center</title>
 <graphic scalefit="1" width="80%" fileref="illustrations40/ucc-app-center.png"/>
 </figure>

<para>
  A UCC environment is made up of three components:
  <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><simpara>
	  The integration in the UCS management system (UMC modules and LDAP schema extensions). They
	  are automatically installed on the &ucsMaster; and all &ucsBackup; via the Univention App Center.
	</simpara></listitem>

	<listitem><simpara>
	  A UCS server which distributes the images for the installation of UCC systems via PXE. The
	  images used for the installation of UCC systems are loaded from the Univention mirror using
	  &ucsUMC; module and then distributed locally to the clients.
	  UCC servers can be installed in all UCS server roles (&ucsMaster;, &ucsBackup;, &ucsSlave; and
	  &ucsMember;). It is possible to employ more than one UCC server in an environment.
	</simpara></listitem>

	<listitem><simpara>
	  The UCC clients. They are installed via the images provided by Univention.
	</simpara></listitem>

  </itemizedlist>
</para>

<para>
  UCC clients use the 32-bit Intel architecture (i386). We recommend also installing the UCS server
  with the i386 architecture. The reasoning for this is that a system with the same architecture is
  required for the build of adapted UCC images (see <xref linkend="imagegen:chapter"/>). If only the
  official UCC images are used (or if the UCC images are built on another system), the UCS server
  can also be installed with the amd64 architecture.
</para>

<section id="installation:installation">
  <title>Installation</title>
  <para>
	The UCC server can be installed on any UCS server role (&ucsMaster;, &ucsBackup;, &ucsSlave; or
	&ucsMember;). All available errata updates should be installed on that system.
  </para>

  <para>
	In the Univention App Center, select the <emphasis>Univention Corporate Client</emphasis>
	application and click on <guimenu>Install</guimenu>. The integration in the UCS management
	system (UMC modules and LDAP schema extensions) are automatically installed on the
	&ucsMaster; and all &ucsBackup; via the Univention App Center.
  </para>

  <para>
	Once the component is installed, click on <guimenu>Restart</guimenu>.
  </para>

  <para>
	The join scripts are automatically run on &ucsMaster; and &ucsBackup; systems during the
	installation of the UCC app. The <guimenu>Domain join</guimenu> UMC module must be run on
	&ucsSlave; and &ucsMember; installations and the <guimenu>Execute all pending join
	scripts</guimenu> option selected for the UCC server to be ready for use.
  </para>

  <para>
	Following the installation, the initial configuration is performed via a wizard in the &ucsUMC;
	(see <xref linkend="umc:initialsetup"/>) or via manually configured policies. The UCS wizard is
	recommended for the initial setup for small to medium-sized installations.
  </para>

  <para>
	UCC can be installed on more than one server, e.g., if UCC clients are to be operated at more
	than one site. Further information can be found in <xref linkend="rollout:bootpolicy"/>.
  </para>

</section>


<section id="installation:officialimages">
  <title>Official UCC images</title>
  <para>
	Univention provides two preconfigured UCC images: a minimal image for thin clients and a larger
	image for native desktop installations. These two images are maintained and tested by Univention.
	The images are downloaded via a &ucsUMC; module, see <xref linkend="installation:imagemanagement:download"/>.
  </para>

  <para>
	UCC systems operated with these images must have at least 512 MB of system memory available.
	Since UCC 2.0 is based on Ubuntu 14.04, all x86 desktop hardware which is supported in Ubuntu
	14.04 is also supported in Univention Corporate Client. You can either test whether your device is
	compatible or contact the hardware supplier for compatibility information.
  </para>

  <para>
	The thin client image offers a minimal desktop and support for accessing terminal sessions on
	Windows and UCC terminal servers. UCC thin client images integrate the Citrix Receiver for accessing
	Citrix terminal services. In addition, a local LXDE desktop environment is also
	available. Thin clients which are to be operated with this image must be equipped with at least 2
	GB of local disk space (e.g., CompactFlash or SSD).
  </para>

  <para>
	The desktop client image offers a KDE Plasma desktop and support for terminal sessions to Windows
	and UCC terminal servers (support for Citrix XenApp can be subsequently installed).
	In addition, the desktop image is also the basis for the operation of an XRDP terminal server
	(see <xref linkend="terminalservices:xrdp"/>).
  </para>

  <para>
	Software packages can also be installed or removed to complement the
	range of functions of the standard UCC images. Software updates can
	also be initiated through a policy (see <xref linkend="config:softwareupdates"/>)
  </para>
</section>

<section id="installation:imagemanagement:download">
  <title>Downloading/removing UCC images</title>

  <para>
	The UCC images are not delivered in the Debian package format (the format is not best-suited to
	files in the gigabyte range). Instead, UCC images can be downloaded via the &ucsUMC; module <guimenu>UCC Images</guimenu>. A list of
	all available images is shown when the module is started. Already downloaded images are shown as
	<guimenu>installed</guimenu>; not yet installed images as <guimenu>available</guimenu>. Each
	image is furnished with a version number; the official UCC images are updated regularly and -
	if available - shown with an updated version number. The <guimenu>Download</guimenu> and
	<guimenu>Remove</guimenu> options can be used to add and remove images.
  </para>

  <para>
  </para>

  <para>
	The images are downloaded from <ulink url="http://ucc-images.software-univention.de/download/ucc-images/"/>. A local UCC mirror can
	also be used, see <xref linkend="installation:imagemanagement:mirror"/>.
  </para>

  <para>
	Alternatively, images can also be managed via command line tools:
	<command>ucc-image-download</command> can be used to download images. The individual files of
	the image are referenced via a specification file containing the file names and SHA-256 hashes. The hash
	values are checked as part of the download procedure in order to detect erroneous
	transmissions. The parameter <option>-s</option> is used to provide the name of the specification
	file on the mirror. The full list of available parameters can be queried with the
	<option>-h</option> option. The <command>ucc-image-remove -l</command> command can be used
	to output an overview of the available images. An image can be deleted using the parameter
	<option>-r</option> and specifying a specification file.
  </para>

  <section id="installation:imagemanagement:rootpw">
	<title>Setting the initial root password for UCC images</title>
	<para>
	  The root password of the installed UCC system is initially specified in the image. To avoid
	  there being an identical root password on all UCC systems operated with the official
	  Univention images, the root password is "personalised" during the image download: the root
	  password of the UCS server is set as the root password on the images.  For existing images,
	  the root password can be set subsequently with the command
	  <command>ucc-image-root-password</command>, e.g.

	  <programlisting language="sh">
ucc-image-root-password -i ucc-2.1-desktop-image.img -p
	  </programlisting>
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="installation:imagemanagement:mirror">
	<title>Operating a local UCC image mirror</title>
	<para>
	  If you are running a number of UCC servers or an infrastructure completely disconnected from
	  the Internet, you can also operate a local UCC mirror. In this case, the images need to be
	  stored on an HTTP server. Then the &ucsUCRV; <envar>ucc/image/download/url</envar> on the UCC
	  servers needs to be set to the download path.
	</para>
  </section>
</section>


</chapter>
