<chapter id="installation:chapter">
<title>Installation</title>
<para>
  Univention Corporate Client integrates into the management system
  of Univention Corporate Server. UCS 3.2 is a prerequisite for the
  installation of UCC.
</para>

<para>
  The UCS integration packages are installed via the Univention App
  Center. General information on the Univention App Center can be found
  in the UCS manual <biblioref linkend="ucs-manual"/>.
</para>

<figure><title>Installing UCC in the Univention App Center</title>
 <graphic scalefit="1" width="60%" fileref="illustrations/ucc-app-center.png"/>
 </figure>

<para>
  A UCC environment is made up of three components:
  <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><simpara>
	  The integration in the UCS management system (UMC modules and LDAP schema extensions). They
	  are installed on the &ucsMaster; and all &ucsBackup; via the Univention App Center.
	</simpara></listitem>

	<listitem><simpara>
	  A UCS server which distributes the images for the installation of UCC systems via PXE. The
	  images used for the installation of UCC systems are loaded from the Univention mirror using
	  &ucsUMC; module and then distributed locally to the clients. 
	  UCC servers can be installed in all UCS server roles (&ucsMaster;, &ucsBackup;, &ucsSlave; and
	  &ucsMember;). It is possible to employ more than one UCC server in an environment.
	</simpara></listitem>

	<listitem><simpara>
	  The UCC clients. They are installed via the images provided by Univention.
	</simpara></listitem>

  </itemizedlist>
</para>


<section id="installation:singleserver">
  <title>Installation in a single-server environment</title>
  <para>
	The UCC server can be installed on any UCS server role (&ucsMaster;, &ucsBackup;, &ucsSlave; or
	&ucsMember;). All available errata updates should be installed on that system.
  </para>

  <para>
	In the Univention App Center, select the <emphasis>Univention Corporate Client</emphasis>
	application and click on <guimenu>Install</guimenu>.
  </para>

  <para>
	Once the component is installed, click on <guimenu>Restart</guimenu>.
  </para>

  <para>
	It is recommended to restart the system before the rollout of UCC clients.
  </para>

</section>

<section id="installation:distributed">
  <title>Installation in a distributed environment</title>
  <para>
	When UCC is installed in an environment with more than one server,
	the installation is performed in two stages:
  </para>

  <para>
	All available errata updates should be installed on both the
	&ucsMaster; and the additional server.
  </para>

  <para>
	1. Installation of the UMC modules and LDAP schema expansions:
  </para>

  <para>
	Log on to the &ucsMaster; as the <emphasis>root</emphasis> user and  run the following
	command. If &ucsBackup; systems are in use, the  command must also be run on all of these
	systems. After installation the &ucsUMC; server needs to be restarted:

	<programlisting>
univention-add-app --latest ucc ucc-server
/etc/init.d/univention-management-console-server restart
	</programlisting>
  </para>

  <para>
	2. Installation of the UCC server(s)
  </para>

  <para>
	UCC servers can be installed in all UCS server roles. The UMC module <guimenu>Univention App
	Center</guimenu> must be opened on all the systems on which you wish to install a UCC server.
  </para>

  <para>
	In the Univention App Center, select the <emphasis>Univention Corporate Client</emphasis>
	application and click on <guimenu>Install</guimenu>.
  </para>

  <para>
	Once the component is installed, click on <guimenu>Restart</guimenu>.
  </para>

  <para>
	Finally the join scripts need to be executed on the UCC server:
	<programlisting>
	  univention-run-join-scripts
	</programlisting>
  </para>

  <para>
	It is recommended to restart the system before the rollout of UCC clients.
  </para>
</section>


<section id="installation:officialimages">
  <title>Official UCC images</title>
  <para>
	Univention provides two preconfigured UCC images: a minimal image for thin clients and a larger
	image for native desktop installations. These two images are maintained and tested by Univention.
	<!-- Die Images werden über ein &ucsUMC;-Modul verwaltet, siehe <xref linkend="installation:imagemanagement:download"/>. -->
  </para>

  <para>
	UCC systems operated with these images must have at least 512 MB of system memory available.
  </para>

  <para>
	The thin client image offers a minimal desktop and support for accessing terminal sessions on
	Windows and UCC terminal servers. In addition, a local LXDE desktop environment is also
	available. Thin clients which are to be operated with this image must be equipped with at least 2
	GB of local disk space (e.g., CompactFlash or SSD).
  </para>

  <para>
	The desktop client image offers a KDE Plasma desktop and support for terminal sessions to Windows
	and UCC terminal servers (support for Citrix XenApp can be subsequently installed).
	In addition, the desktop image is also the basis for the operation of an XRDP terminal server.
  </para>

  <para>
	Software packages can also be installed or removed to complement the
	range of functions of the standard UCC images. Software updates can
	also be initiated through a policy (see <xref linkend="config:softwareupdates"/>)
  </para>
</section>

<section id="installation:imagemanagement:download">
  <title>Downloading/removing UCC images</title>

  <!-- <para> -->
  <!-- 	UCC-Images können über das &ucsUMC;-Modul <guimenu>UCC Images</guimenu> heruntergeladen -->
  <!-- 	werden. Nach dem Start des Moduls wird eine Liste aller verfügbaren Images abgezeigt. Bereits -->
  <!-- 	geladene Images werden als <guimenu>installed</guimenu> angezeigt, nicht installierte Images als -->
  <!-- 	<guimenu>available</guimenu>. Jedes Image ist mit einer Versionsnummer versehen; die offiziellen -->
  <!-- 	UCC-Images werden regelmässig aktualisiert und - wenn verfügbar - mit einer aktuelleren -->
  <!-- 	Versionsnummer angezeigt. Über die Optionen <guimenu>Download</guimenu> und -->
  <!-- 	<guimenu>Remove</guimenu> können images hinzugefügt oder entfernt werden. -->
  <!-- </para> -->

  <para>
	The UCC images are not delivered in the Debian package format; the Debian package format is not
	best-suited to files in the gigabyte range.
  </para>

  <para>
	The images are downloaded from <ulink url="http://ucc-images.software-univention.de/download/ucc-images/"/>. A local UCC mirror can
	also be used, see <xref linkend="installation:imagemanagement:mirror"/>.
  </para>

  <para>
	Alternatively, images can also be managed via command line tools:
	<command>ucc-image-download</command> can be used to download images. The individual files of
	the image are referenced via a spec file containing the file names and SHA256 hashes. The hash
	values are checked as part of the download procedure in order to detect erroneous
	transmissions. The parameter <emphasis>-s</emphasis> is used to provide the name of the spec
	file on the mirror. The full list of available parameters can be queried with the
	<emphasis>-h</emphasis> option. The <command>ucc-image-remove -l</command> command can be used
	to output an overview of the available images. An image can be deleted using the parameter
	<emphasis>-r</emphasis> and specifying a spec file.
  </para>

  <section id="installation:imagemanagement:rootpw">
	<title>Setting the initial root password for UCC images</title>
	<para>
	  The root password of the installed UCC system is initially specified in the image. To avoid
	  there being an identical root password on all UCC systems operated with the official
	  Univention images, the root password is "personalised" during the image download: the root
	  password of the UCS server is set as the root password on the images.  For existing images,
	  the root password can be set subsequently with the command
	  <command>ucc-image-root-password</command>, e.g.

	  <programlisting>
ucc-image-root-password -i ucc-2.0-desktop-image.img -p
	  </programlisting>
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="installation:imagemanagement:mirror">
	<title>Operating a local UCC image mirror</title>
	<para>
	  If you are running a number of UCC servers or an infrastructure completely disconnected from
	  the Internet, you can also operate a local UCC mirror. In this case, the images need to be
	  stored on an HTTP server. Then the &ucsUCRV; <envar>ucc/image/download/url</envar> on the UCC
	  servers needs to be set to the download path.
	</para>
  </section>
</section>


</chapter>
