<chapter id="installation:chapter">
<title>Installation</title>
<para>
  Univention Corporate Client integrates into the management system
  of Univention Corporate Server. UCS 3.1 is a prerequisite for the
  installation of UCC.
</para>
<para>
  The UCS integration packages are installed via the Univention App
  Center. General information on the Univention App Center can be found
  in the UCS manual <biblioref linkend="ucs-manual"/>.
</para>

<figure><title>Installing UCC in the Univention App Center</title>
 <graphic scalefit="1" width="60%" fileref="illustrations/ucc-app-center.png"/>
 </figure>

<para>
  A UCC environment is made up of three components:
  <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><simpara>The integration in the UCS management system (UMC
	modules and LDAP schema extensions). These must be installed on
	the &ucsMaster; and all &ucsBackup; systems.</simpara></listitem>
	<listitem><simpara>A UCS server which distributes the images for the
	installation of UCC systems via PXE. The images used for the installation of
	UCC systems are loaded from the Univention mirror using an image
	download tool and then distributed locally to the clients. Custom
	installation images are also created on UCS servers. UCC
	servers can be installed in all UCS server roles (&ucsMaster;, &ucsBackup;,
	&ucsSlave; and &ucsMember;). It is possible to employ
	more than one UCC server in an environment.</simpara></listitem>
	<listitem><simpara>The UCC clients. They are installed via the
	images.</simpara></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</para>


<section id="installation:singleserver">
<title>Installation in a single-server environment</title>
<para>
  All available errata updates should be installed on the
  &ucsMaster;.
</para>
<para>
  In the Univention App Center, select the <emphasis>Univention Corporate
  Client</emphasis> application and click on
  <guimenu>Install</guimenu>.
</para>

<para>
  The thin client image is downloaded during the installation; the
  download may take some time depending on the speed of the Internet
  connection.
</para>
<para>
  Once the component is installed, click on
  <guimenu>Restart</guimenu>.
</para>
<para>
  It is recommended to restart the system before the rollout of UCC clients.
</para>

</section>

<section id="installation:distributed">
<title>Installation in a distributed environment</title>
<para>
  When UCC is installed in an environment with more than one server,
  the installation is performed in two stages:
</para>
<para>
  All available errata updates should be installed on both the
  &ucsMaster; and the additional server.
</para>
<para>
1. Installation of the UMC modules and LDAP schema expansions:
</para>
<para>
  Log on to the &ucsMaster; as the <emphasis>root</emphasis> user and
  run the following command. If &ucsBackup; systems are in use, the
  command must also be run on all of these systems. After installation
  the &ucsUMC; server needs to be restarted:

  <programlisting>
univention-add-app --latest ucc ucc-management-integration
/etc/init.d/univention-management-console-server restart
  </programlisting>
</para>


<para>
  2. Installation of the UCC server(s)
</para>
<para>
  UCC servers can be installed in all UCS server roles. The UMC module
  <guimenu>Univention App Center</guimenu> must be opened on all the
  systems on which you wish to install a UCC server.
</para>
<para>
  In the Univention App Center, select the <emphasis>Univention Corporate
  Client</emphasis> application and click on
  <guimenu>Install</guimenu>. The thin client image is downloaded
  during the installation; the download may take some time depending
  on the speed of the Internet connection.
</para>
<para>
  Once the component is installed, click on <guimenu>Restart</guimenu>.
</para>
<para>
  Finally the join scripts need to be executed on the UCC server:
  <programlisting>
univention-run-join-scripts
  </programlisting>
</para>
<para>
  It is recommended to restart the system before the rollout of UCC clients.
</para>


</section>


<section id="installation:imagemanagement">
<title>Management of UCC images</title>

<section id="installation:imagemanagement:download">
<title>Downloading UCC images</title>
<para>
  The UCC images are not delivered in the Debian package format; the
  Debian package format is not best suited to files in the gigabyte
  range.
</para>
<para>
  Instead, UCC images are downloaded with the
  <command>ucc-image-download</command> tool. The individual files of
  the image are referenced via a spec file containing the file names
  and SHA256 hashes. The hash values are checked as part of the
  download procedure in order to detect erroneous transmissions. The
  proxy settings of a UCS system are taken into account.
</para>
<para>
  The images are available at
  <ulink url="http://ucc-images.software-univention.de/download/ucc-images/"/>. A
  local UCC mirror can also be used, see <xref linkend="installation:imagemanagement:mirror"/>.
</para>
<para>
  Univention provides two metapackages, the installation of which
  initiates the downloading of the images. The packages can be
  installed with <command>univention-install</command> or via the
  software management module of the &ucsUMC;.

  <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><simpara><emphasis>ucc-thinclient-image</emphasis>
	installs the latest thin client image</simpara></listitem>
	<listitem><simpara><emphasis>ucc-desktop-image</emphasis> installs
	the latest desktop image</simpara></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</para>
<para>
  The installation of the images is initiated at the end of the
  installation. The downloaded images are not removed when removing
  the metapackages. If desired, they should be removed manually in the
  directory <filename>/var/lib/univention-client-boot</filename>.
</para>
<para>
  Alternatively, the download can also be performed manually by
  running <command>ucc-image-download</command>. The parameter
  <emphasis>-s</emphasis> is used to provide the name of the spec file
  on the mirror, e.g.:
  <programlisting>
ucc-image-download -s ucc-1.0-thinclient-image.img.spec
  </programlisting>
</para>
<para>
  Interrupted downloads are restarted as standard. You can use the
  option <emphasis>--reload</emphasis> to force the download to
  restart completely.
</para>
<para>
  The full list of available parameters can be queried with the
  <emphasis>-h</emphasis> option.
</para>
<para>
  The root password of the installed system is initially specified in
  the image. To avoid there being an identical root password on all
  UCC systems operated with the official Univention images, the root password
  is "personalised" during the image download: the root password of
  the UCC server is set as the root password on the images. You can
  also use the <emphasis>--set-root-pw-interactive</emphasis> option of the
  <command>ucc-image-download</command> command to set a different root password.
</para>

<para>
  For existing images, the root password can be set subsequently with the command
  <command>ucc-image-root-password</command>, e.g.

  <programlisting>
ucc-image-root-password -i ucc-1.0-rev2-desktop-image.img -p
  </programlisting>
</para>
</section>

<section id="installation:imagemanagement:remove">
<title>Deleting UCC images</title>
<para>
  The <command>ucc-image-remove -l</command> command can be used to
  output an overview of the available images. An image can be deleted
  using the parameter <emphasis>-r</emphasis> and specifying a spec
  file, e.g.:
  <programlisting>
ucc-image-remove -r ucc-1.0-desktop-image.img.spec
  </programlisting>
</para>
</section>

<section id="installation:imagemanagement:mirror">
<title>Operating a local UCC image mirror</title>
<para>
  If you are operating a number of UCC servers or an infrastructure
  completely disconnected from the Internet, you can also operate a
  local UCC mirror. In this case, the images need to be stored on an
  HTTP server. Then the &ucsUCRV; <envar>ucc/image/download/url</envar> on the UCC
  servers needs to be set to the download path.
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section id="installation:officialimages">
<title>Official UCC images</title>
<para>
  Univention provides two preconfigured UCC images: a
  minimal image for thin clients and a larger image for native desktop
  installations. These two images are maintained and tested
  by Univention.
</para>

<para>
  UCC systems operated with these images must have at least 512 MB of
  system memory available.
</para>

<para>
  The thin client image offers a minimal desktop and support for
  terminal sessions on Windows and UCC terminal servers. In addition, a local LXDE desktop environment is also
  available. Thin clients which are to be operated with this image
  must be equipped with at least 2 GB of local disk space (e.g.,
  CompactFlash or SSD).
</para>

<para>
  The desktop client image offers a KDE Plasma desktop and support for
  terminal sessions on Windows and UCC terminal servers (support for
  Citrix XenApp can be subsequently installed).
</para>

<para>
  Software packages can also be installed or removed to complement the
  range of functions of the standard UCC images. Software updates can
  also be initiated through a policy (see <xref linkend="config:softwareupdates"/>)
</para>



</section>

</chapter>
