<chapter id="introduction:chapter">
<title>Introduction</title>

<para>
  Univention Corporate Client (UCC) is a flexible and economic
  alternative for the operation and administration of PCs, notebooks
  and thin clients in companies and institutions. The software
  contains a Linux-based desktop environment optimised for business
  use. In addition, UCC serves as a platform for access to remote
  desktop solutions and virtualized desktops as well as browser or
  terminal server-based applications.
</para>

<para>
  UCC systems are rolled out via an image-based approach: All the
  user data - and as such also the user settings - are stored on a
  separate partition. If a new version of the image is installed, the
  complete operating system installation is overwritten.
</para>

<para>
  UCC clients are part of a UCS domain. The clients are
  entirely managed through settings from the LDAP. As a result, a UCC
  system is ready to use after an upgrade or an
  installation. Features configured from the LDAP include network
  configuration, hardware settings like dual monitor setups and
  software selections.
</para>

<para>
  Kubuntu is used as the basis for the images (Version 14.04 in UCC
  2.0). Univention provides two preconfigured images: a
  minimal image for thin clients and a larger image for desktop
  installations. These two images are maintained and tested
  by Univention. It is also possible to create modified or completely
  new images with a minimum of effort using the included image toolkit
  (see <xref linkend="imagegen:toolkit"/>). In contrast to the
  integration of Ubuntu clients in UCS, UCC clients work out
  of the box and require no further modification.
</para>

<para>
  UCC systems include the most important UCS base components and
  integrate into the UCS user management: all users in a UCS
  domain can log on to UCC clients using their domain password. The
  integration packages are installed via the Univention App
  Center.
</para>

<para>
  UCC integrates terminal services provided via XRDP, i.e., the KDE Linux desktop is provided via
  the RDP protocol. The KDE desktop can be accessed from UCC thin clients or any other RDP client.
</para>

<para>
  UCC supports both a local desktop based on KDE Plasma and working on terminal servers (RDP, Citrix
  XenApp and remotely used KDE desktops based on XRDP). Access to web-based services can also be
  configured using a full-screen Firefox browser session. A UCC desktop system be used both in the
  company network and in mobile use (all user and group information are cached locally for that).
</para>

<para>
  A UCC system is usually installed over a network using PXE. The rollout
  can be performed fully automatic without user interaction (see <xref
  linkend="rollout:automatic"/>).
</para>

<para>
  The CompactFlash storage media typically integrated in thin clients
  are only designed for a limited number of write operations.
  Thin clients in UCC are thus started with an OverlayFS file system
  so that all write accesses on the storage media of a booted system
  are only performed in the system memory and not written to the hard
  drive. All the write changes are thus lost once the thin client is
  switched off. This does not pose any problems for access to terminal
  services, as all the user activities are performed on the respective
  terminal servers. The system log of UCC clients is performed
  remotely.
</para>

</chapter>
