<chapter id="terminalservices:chapter">
  <title>Terminal services with UCC</title>

  <para>
	In addition to the operation of stationary UCC clients, UCC also supports
	access to terminal services. Login is supported to:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><simpara>UCC terminal servers via the RDP protocol (based on xrdp)</simpara></listitem>
	  <listitem><simpara>Windows terminal services via the RDP protocol</simpara></listitem>
	  <listitem><simpara>Citrix XenApp</simpara></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
  </para>

  <para>
	There are three possibilities for configuring access to a terminal service:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><simpara>
		An interactive selection of the session by the user during login to LightDM (see <xref
		linkend="logins:sessions"/>)
	  </simpara></listitem>
	  
	  <listitem><simpara>
		Automatic session selection where login is performed with a guest user. In this case, no
		login dialogue is shown (see <xref linkend="logins:autologin"/>).
	  </simpara></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
  </para>

  <section id="terminalservices:xrdp">
	<title>UCC terminal services based on XRDP</title>
	<para>
	  UCC integrates terminal services provided via XRDP, i.e., the KDE Linux desktop is provided
	  via the RDP protocol. 
	</para>

	<section id="terminalservices:xrdp:installation">
	  <title>Installation</title>

	  <para>
	  </para>

	  <para>
		UCC terminal servers are installed with the UCC desktop image. The setup is described in
		<xref linkend="umc:manageucc"/>. The <package>univention-xrdp</package> package must also be
		installed on the desktop image. There is a UCC software policy linked to the container
		<emphasis>cn=computers, cn=ucc-xrdpserver</emphasis> (see <xref
		linkend="config:softwareupdates"/>), i.e., if the computer object is created in the container,
		the package is installed automatically during the rollout of the UCC system.
	  </para>

	  <caution>
	  	<para>
		  An XRDP terminal server needs to be restarted once following the installation to be able
		  to initialise additional PulseAudio drivers correctly!
	  	</para>
	  </caution>

	</section>

	<section id="terminalservices:xrdp:access">
	  <title>Accessing XRDP terminal services</title>

	  <para>
		The access of an XRDP terminal server from a UCC thin client via the RDP protocol is
		described in <xref linkend="terminalservices:rdp"/>. 
	  </para>

	  <para>
		If the forwarding of storage devices is enabled, they appear in the user's home directory in
		the <filename>.~/xrdp_client</filename> directory. Forwarding of sound output in terminal sessions is also
		possible. This requires a sound card to be present or emulated on the XRDP terminal server.
	  </para>

	  <para>
		Access to the XRDP terminal server from other clients is also supported (e.g., Windows PCs,
		Mac OS X or thin clients with third-party operating systems). For these clients it is
		sufficient to configure the IP address or hostname of the XDRP server and perform a login
		with a user from the UCS domain. An XRDP login screen is provided for the login from
		external devices. It is not necessary to specify a domain when logging on to an XDRP
		terminal server.
	  </para>

	  <para>
		Password changes are currently not yet supported when logging in from an external device. If
		the password has expired, the login will fail. Password changes are performed in the login
		manager LightDM when logging in from UCC thin clients.
	  </para>
	</section>


	<section id="terminalservices:xrdp:kdeprofile">
	  <title>KDE desktop in UCC terminal services</title>
	  <para>
		As standard, UCC uses a KDE profile optimised for remote operation on terminal servers. It
		disables e.g. update notifications. The use of this profile can be disabled per UCC terminal
		server by setting the &ucsUCRV; on the XRDP terminal server <envar>ucc/session/remote/profile</envar> to
		<emphasis>false</emphasis> (see <xref linkend="config:ucr"/>). 
	  </para>
	</section>
  </section>

  <section id="terminalservices:rdp">
	<title>Windows terminal services (RDP)</title>
	<para>
	  UCC supports login to Windows 2003/2008/2012-based Windows terminal servers via the RDP
	  protocol. The Windows terminal servers can be joined in the UCS domain or alternatively the access
	  can be performed against an external domain.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The login is performed via the <emphasis>RDP</emphasis> session script which uses the
	  NeutrinoRDP client (a fork of the freerdp code base). The password entered
	  by the user during login to LightDM is cached by a PAM module and automatically provided to
	  NeutrinoRDP, i.e., it is not necessary to enter it again when logging in to the terminal server.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The RDP client Remmina is provided as a client with which an RDP connection can be
	  configured and started on the desktop.
	</para>

	<section id="terminalservices:rdp:setup">
	  <title>Installation</title>

	  <para>
		The session script for RDP (<package>univention-ucc-session-rdp</package>) is installed on
		desktop systems and thin clients in the default setting.
	  </para>

	  <section id="terminalservices:rdp:umc">
		<title>Installation using the setup wizard</title>

		<para>
		  For setting up the RDP access to RDP terminal servers, the <guimenu>UCC Setup</guimenu>
		  wizard must be opened in the &ucsUMC;. The <guimenu>Configure access to a Windows/XRDP
		  terminal server</guimenu> option must be selected under <guimenu>Thin client
		  configuration</guimenu> in the <guimenu>Configuration of terminal services</guimenu>
		  submenu.
		</para>

		<para>
		  The host name of the RDP terminal server must be entered in the <guimenu>Host name of
		  terminal server</guimenu> input field. If a Windows terminal server is used, the domain
		  name must be entered in the <guimenu>Domain name</guimenu> input field. If XRDP is used,
		  the field may be left blank.
		</para>

		<para>
		  If sound is to be transmitted to the accessing client from the terminal session, the
		  <guimenu>Enable sound</guimenu> option must be enabled. The sound output in the RDP
		  session is transmitted via an RDP session channel.
		</para>

		<para>
		  USB storage devices (USB sticks or CD/DVD drives), which can be inserted in the thin
		  client, can be passed through to the RDP session. This is done by enabling the
		  <guimenu>Enable USB storage passthrough</guimenu> option. Further details on the mounting
		  of devices can be found in <xref linkend="hardware:usbthin"/>. The transmission is
		  performed via a session channel of the RDP protocol.
		</para>
	  </section>


	  <section id="terminalservices:rdp:setup:manually">
		<title>Installation without the UMC wizard</title>

		<para>
		  The terminal server and the Windows domain of the terminal server can be specified per
		  user via a <emphasis>UCC user session</emphasis> user policy. Alternatively, the server
		  and the domain can also be specified per client by setting the &ucsUCR; variables
		  <envar>rdp/domainname</envar> and <envar>rdp/server</envar>. If an XRDP server is used as
		  the terminal server, the <envar>rdp/domainname</envar> can be left blank.
		</para>

		<para>
		  Mass storage devices mounted on the thin client (see <xref linkend="hardware:usbthin"/>)
		  is available in the RDP session if the &ucsUCRV; <envar>rdp/redirectdisk</envar> is set to
		  <emphasis>true</emphasis>. 
		</para>

		<para>
		  Sound output is enabled by default. It can be disabled by setting the &ucsUCRV;
		  <envar>rdp/disable-sound</envar> to <emphasis>true</emphasis>.
		</para>
	  </section>


	  <section id="terminalservices:rdp:setup:advanced">
		<title>Advanced configuration</title>

		<section id="terminalservices:rdp:crypto">
		  <title>Networklevel authentication / certificate approval</title>
		  <para>
			The RDP client uses the "Network Level Authentication" (NLA) authentication
			method as standard. This can be disabled by setting the &ucsUCRV; <envar>rdp/checknla</envar> to
			<emphasis>false</emphasis>.
		  </para>

		  <para>
			Verification of the login certificate is also disabled as standard. It can be enabled by
			setting the &ucsUCRV; <envar>rdp/ignorecertificate</envar> to <emphasis>true</emphasis>.
		  </para>

		  <para>
			In special cases, it may be necessary to disable the TLS encryption of the RDP
			connection entirely. This is done by setting the &ucsUCRV; <envar>rdp/tlsencryption</envar>
			to <emphasis>false</emphasis>.
		  </para>
		</section>

		<section id="terminalservices:rdp:furtheropts">
		  <title>Further configuration options for the RDP session</title>

		  <para>
			The &ucsUCRV; <envar>rdp/keyboard</envar> can be used to configure a different keyboard
			layout for the RDP session from that of the current client. The layout is specified in
			the same format as the &ucsUCRV; <envar>xorg/keyboard/options/XkbLayout</envar>.
		  </para>

		  <para>
			<envar>rdp/user</envar> can be used to specify a different user name from the current
			one during login.
		  </para>

		  <para>
			The &ucsUCRV; <envar>rdp/additionaloptions</envar> can be used to provide any additional
			options to neutrinordp (e.g., to enable additional plugins).
		  </para>

		  <para>
			<envar>rdp/geometry</envar> can be used to specify the screen resolution.
		  </para>

		</section>

	  </section>
	</section>
  </section>

  <section id="terminalservices:citrix">
	  <title>Citrix XenApp terminal services</title>
	  <para>
		UCC supports access to Citrix XenApp terminal servers. This documentation refers to Citrix
		XenApp and Citrix Receiver 13.1.
	  </para>

	  <para>
		Citrix XenApp supports two login methods:
		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem><simpara>Access to the XenApp terminal server is
		  configured by an ICA session file in which the connection
		  parameters are configured.</simpara></listitem>
		  <listitem><simpara>The access is performed via a Citrix Farm web
		  interface the user logs in to. During the login, an ICA file
		  tailored to the user is generated, which is started via a browser
		  plugin in the Citrix Receiver client.</simpara></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	  </para>
	  <para>
		UCC only integrates the browser-based login method.
	  </para>

	  <para>
		Access to a Citrix terminal service is performed via the <emphasis>XenApp</emphasis> session
		script. This opens a fullscreen Firefox session with the login web interface of the Citrix
		installation. If the browser is closed, a menu opens in which you are offered the
		possibility to log in to Citrix again, shutdown the thin client or select another session.
	  </para>

<section id="terminalservices:citrix:setup">
  <title>Installation</title>

  <section id="terminalservices:citrix:setup:umc">
	<title>Installation using the setup wizard</title>
	<para>
	  For setting up access to a Citrix XenApp terminal service, the <guimenu>UCC Setup</guimenu>
	  wizard must be opened in the &ucsUMC;. The <guimenu>Configure access to a Citrix XenApp
	  terminal server</guimenu> option must be selected under <guimenu>Thin client
	  configuration</guimenu> in the <guimenu>Configuration of terminal services</guimenu> submenu.
	</para>

	<para>
	  For licensing reasons it is not possible to deliver the Citrix Receiver with Univention
	  Corporate Client. Instead, it must be downloaded for the 32 bit Intel architecture as a DEB file using the download link provided
	  and saved in a local directory. Only Citrix Receiver 13.1 is supported in UCC 2.0.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The UCC thin client image in which you wish to install the Citrix Receiver must now be
	  selected in the <guimenu>Please select the image(..)</guimenu> field. After clicking on
	  <guimenu>Upload</guimenu> and selecting the DEB file of the Citrix Receiver, it will be automatically
	  integrated in the UCC image.
	</para>

	<para>
	  In the default setting, each user of the Citrix terminal server must confirm the end user
	  license agreement (EULA) the first time he/she accesses the terminal server. If the
	  <guimenu>Confirm the End User License Agreement of Citrix Receiver</guimenu> option is
	  enabled, the license is confirmed automatically.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The <guimenu>URL for Citrix farm login</guimenu> option is used to configure the URL of the
	  Citrix web interface. The session script then opens the web interface directly in Firefox
	  during login.
	</para>
	
	<para>
	  As the authentication during the Citrix login occurs on the web interface and if Citrix is the
	  only terminal service, it is not necessary for the user to log on to the thin client again. If
	  the <guimenu>Automatic thin client login</guimenu> option is enabled, the login to LightDM
	  occurs automatically.
	</para>
	
  </section>

  <section id="terminalservices:citrix:setup:manually">
	<title>Installation without the UMC wizard</title>
	<para>
	  This section provides a brief description of the setting up of the XenApp for complex
	  scenarios in which the UCC setup wizard should not be used. For general information on XenApp
	  and UCC, please see <xref linkend="terminalservices:citrix:setup:umc"/>
	</para>
	
	<para>
	  The Citrix Receiver for 32 bit systems must be downloaded as a DEB file from <ulink
	  url="http://www.citrix.de/downloads/citrix-receiver/linux/receiver-for-linux-131.html"/>.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The <command>ucc-image-add-citrix-receiver</command> tool can be used to install the Citrix
	  Receiver in a UCC thin client image. The parameter <emphasis>-i</emphasis> specifies the UCC
	  image and <emphasis>-d</emphasis> the DEB file with the Citrix Receiver. The
	  <package>univention-ucc-session-xenapp</package> meta package is installed automatically.
	</para>

	<para>
	  If the EULA is to be confirmed automatically, the &ucsUCRV; <envar>citrix/accepteula</envar>
	  must be set to <emphasis>true</emphasis> by means of a policy. The web interface for the
	  Citrix login must be configured via the <envar>citrix/webinterface</envar> variable.
	</para>

	<para>
	  To configure a login-less access to the web interface the &ucsUCRV;
	  <envar>lightdm/autologin/session</envar> must be set to <emphasis>XenApp</emphasis> and the
	  &ucsUCRV; <envar>lightdm/autologin</envar> to <emphasis>yes</emphasis>.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="terminalservices:citrix:setup:advanced">
	<title>Advanced configuration</title>

	<para>
	  The Citrix Receiver uses <filename>/dev/random</filename> as a
	  randomness source as standard. <filename>/dev/random</filename> blocks access if insufficient entropy is
	  available from hardware sources. This is the case on many thin clients. 
	  If the &ucsUCRV; <envar>citrix/linkdevrandom</envar> is set to <emphasis>true</emphasis>,
	  <filename>/dev/random</filename> is converted to a symbolic link to
	  <filename>/dev/urandom</filename> which prevents these delays.
	</para>

	<para>
	  In the default setting, the Citrix Receiver accesses the thin client's sound card(s) via the
	  ALSA interface. For special cases - e.g., systems with multiple sound cards - the &ucsUCRV;
	  <envar>citrix/pulseaudio</envar> can be set to <emphasis>true</emphasis>. The result of this
	  is that the PulseAudio sound daemon is started in the XenApp session script (this e.g.
	  ensures the assignment of a primary sound card).
	</para>

  </section>
</section>


<section id="terminalservices:citrix:soundusb">
<title>Sound transmission / Access to USB storage devices on the thin client</title>
<para>
  Configuration parameters such as full screen display or the
  sound transmission are configured in the Citrix Farm settings. They
  are then saved in the ICA file generated for the user during login
  and implemented by the Citrix Receiver.
</para>
<para>
  An USB storage device on a thin client (see <xref
  linkend="hardware:usbthin"/>) is available under Drive Z: in the
  Citrix session.
</para>
</section>

<section id="terminalservices:citrix:flash">
  <title>Accelerating the playback of Flash videos</title>
  <para>
	The Citrix Receiver offers the possibility of optimising the playback of Flash videos: instead of
	streaming the video on the server and transmitting every image, the video is transmitted to the
	client and played locally in the terminal session. This requires the installation of the Flash
	plugin on the UCC client (the package is called <package>adobe-flashplugin</package>).
  </para>

  <para>
	In the default setting the Flash version on the client and the Flash version on the Citrix server
	need to be identical. Releases of Adobe Flash later than 11.2 are no longer available for Linux.
	The version check can be disabled on the Citrix server. For this a registry key needs to
	be added on the Citrix server in the location <emphasis>HKEY_LOCAL_MACHINE -> Software ->
	Wow6432Node -> Citrix ->  HdxMediaStreamForFlash -> Server -> PseudoServer</emphasis>. The new key
	must be created as a dword, named <emphasis>FlashPlayerVersionComparisonMask</emphasis> and set to
	<emphasis>0</emphasis>.
  </para>

  <para>
	To verify the local Flash playback, you can play a Flash video on the Citrix server and query
	the process list on the UCC client using <command>ps aux</command>. If the Flash redirection is
	working correctly, you should see a process named <emphasis>FlashContainer.bin</emphasis>.
  </para>
</section>

<section id="terminalservices:hdxplayback">
  <title>Windows Media HDX playback</title>
  <para>
    To enable Citrix Windows Media HDX playback on the client the following packages have to 
    installed on the UCC client: gstreamer0.10-plugins-ugly, gstreamer0.10-plugins-good,
    gstreamer0.10-plugins-bad, gstreamer0.10-alsa, gstreamer0.10-fluendo-mp3,
    gstreamer0.10-ffmpeg and gstreamer0.10-x
  </para>
</section>



</section>


</chapter>
