<chapter id="umc:chapter">
<title>Management of UCC systems in the &ucsUMC;</title>

<section id="rollout:administrationumc">
<title>Administration of UCC systems in the &ucsUMC;</title>
<para>
  UCC systems are registered and administrated with the system role
  <emphasis>Univention Corporate Client</emphasis> in the computer
  management module of the &ucsUMC;.
</para>

<para>
  In the command line frontend Univention Directory Manager, clients
  are managed with the <emphasis>computers/ucc</emphasis> module.
</para>
<para>
  The following settings must be configured for every UCC client as a minimum:
  <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><simpara>The <emphasis>name</emphasis> of the client
	(composed of lowercase and uppercase letters, numbers, hyphens and
	underscores).</simpara></listitem>
	<listitem><simpara>The <emphasis>MAC address</emphasis> of the
	client in the notation XX:XX:XX:XX:XX:XX</simpara></listitem>
	<listitem><simpara>The <emphasis>IP address</emphasis> of the client</simpara></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</para>

<figure><title>Management of a UCC system in the UMC</title>
 <graphic scalefit="1" width="100%" fileref="illustrations/ucc-client-umc.png"/>
 </figure>

<para>
  A forward and reverse zone for DNS resolution should be assigned under
  <guimenu>DNS Forward and Reverse Lookup Zone</guimenu>. These zones
  are created automatically in the scope of the installation of the
  &ucsMaster;. The name and the IP address of the UCC client can thus
  also be resolved in the UCS DNS service.
</para>
<para>
  The network configuration of UCC clients is managed through DHCP in
  the default setting. A DHCP service must also be assigned under
  <guimenu>DHCP</guimenu>. These are also created automatically in the
  scope of the installation of the domain controller master. The UCC
  client is then registered for the DHCP server and the configured IP
  address is assigned to the DHCP.
</para>

<para>
  UCS offers you the possibility of centrally managing the IP
  addresses and DNS/DHCP settings of a network in a network
  object in the LDAP. This can considerably facilitate the management of
  UCC clients by selecting the network object in
  <guimenu>Network</guimenu> input field: The next free IP address of
  the network and the DNS and DHCP settings are then adopted automatically.
</para>

<figure><title>Management of IP addresses through a network object</title>
 <graphic scalefit="1" width="80%" fileref="illustrations/umc-network.png"/>
 </figure>

<para>
  During the installation of an UCS system, a network object with the
  name <emphasis>default</emphasis> is saved as standard, which can
  usually be used in normal cases. If, for example, several sites are
  to be managed, additional networks can be defined using the
  <guimenu>Networks</guimenu> wizard in the &ucsUMC;.
</para>
<para>
  The DHCP configuration is then also performed via the UMC. The
  network properties of UCC clients can be centrally specified per
  subnetwork. The settings can be set via the UMC's
  <guimenu>DHCP</guimenu> wizard. The DHCP service of the current
  domain must be selected. The selection list which opens then shows
  the subnetwork object, which can be opened with a click. The
  following properties can be specified under
  <guimenu>Policies</guimenu> amongst others:
  <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><simpara><emphasis>DNS</emphasis> allows the assignment
	of one or more name servers</simpara></listitem>
	<listitem><simpara><emphasis>Routing</emphasis> allows the
	assignment of a default gateway. This must be set to ensure proper routing!</simpara></listitem>
	<listitem><simpara><emphasis>Lease time</emphasis> allows
	configuration of a lease time for an IP address</simpara></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</para>
<para>
  In the default setting, fixed IP addresses are assigned and only to
  clients registered in the LDAP.
</para>
<para>
  The DHCP administration also offers numerous, extensive configuration options,
  which are generally, however, not required in UCC
  client operation. They are described in the DHCP section in the UCS
  manual <biblioref linkend="ucs-manual"/>.
</para>
</section>


<section id="rollout:bootpolicy">
<title>Configuration of the PXE server in a multi-server environment</title>
<para>
  The rollout of UCC systems usually occurs via PXE (see <xref linkend="rollout:imagerollout"/>). If
  UCC is operated in a single server environment the server distributing the IP adresses to the
  clients is identical to the PXE server providing the UCC images for installation.
</para>
<para>
  If UCC is used in a distributed environment, there may be DHCP servers not serving as PXE servers. In
  that case the UCS server distributing the UCC images needs to be configured through a
  <guimenu>DHCP Boot</guimenu> policy. Please see the UCS manual for additional information
  <biblioref linkend="ucs-manual-pxeboot"/>.
</para>
</section>

</chapter>