<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
	  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
	<!ENTITY % extensions SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros.ent" >
	<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros-en.ent" >
	%extensions;
	%entities;
]>
<chapter id="umc:chapter">
  <title>Management of UCC systems in the &ucsUMC;</title>

  <section id="umc:initialsetup">
	<title>Initial setup of a UCC environment</title>
	<para>
	  A &ucsUMC; wizard is provided for the initial configuration of a UCC environment. It guides you
	  through the basic setup of a UCC environment with thin clients and/or desktop
	  clients. Different standard policies are created and configured. The setup wizard is suitable
	  for small to medium-sized environments. The policies can also be manually configured in the
	  &ucsUMC; for more complex requirements in which different policies are to be used for
	  different containers of the LDAP directory or multiple DHCP subnets are to be operated. The
	  policies required for each option are listed in the respective chapters.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The setup wizard is started via the &ucsUMC; module <guimenu>UCC Setup</guimenu>. In the main
	  menu, you can first select whether to set up thin clients and/or desktop systems. UCC
	  images will be downloaded if required.
	</para>

	<para>
	  UCS offers the possibility of centrally managing the IP addresses and DNS/DHCP settings of
	  a network in a network object in the LDAP. This can considerably facilitate the management of
	  IP addresses: When creating a UCC client the next free IP address of the network is selected
	  automatically. Also, DNS and DHCP settings are configured automatically.
	</para>

	<para>
	  In the UCC wizard it is now possible to select an existing network object in the <guimenu>Network
	  configuration</guimenu> dialogue or create a new one. During the installation of a UCS
	  system, a network object with the name <emphasis>default</emphasis> is created as standard.
	  It uses the network of the &ucsMaster;. If only a certain IP segment is to be used for the UCC
	  systems, a new network object can be created with the <guimenu>Specify a new IP
	  segment</guimenu> dialogue. For example, if the IP addresses 192.168.100.100 to
	  192.168.100.200 are used for UCC systems, <emphasis>192.168.100.0</emphasis> must be entered
	  as the <guimenu>Network address</guimenu>, <emphasis>24</emphasis> as the
	  <guimenu>Netmask</guimenu> and <emphasis>192.168.100.100</emphasis> /
	  <emphasis>192.168.100.200</emphasis> entered as the <guimenu>First IP address / Last IP
	  address</guimenu>.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The network configuration of UCC clients is managed through DHCP in nearly all cases
	  The wizard checks whether a default gateway is assigned via DHCP. If this is not the case, a
	  dialogue window opens in which the gateway can be configured. In the default setting, fixed IP
	  addresses are assigned only to clients registered in the LDAP.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The next menu item allows you to select whether desktops and/or thin clients should be
	  configured. No additional configuration is required for Linux desktop systems.
	  The wizards for setting up the thin client access on terminal services are described
	  in the following sections:

	   <itemizedlist>
		 <listitem><simpara>
		   Thin client access to Windows terminal servers (<xref linkend="terminalservices:rdp"/>)
		 </simpara></listitem>

		 <listitem><simpara>
		   Thin client access to Citrix terminal servers (<xref linkend="terminalservices:citrix"/>)
		 </simpara></listitem>

		 <listitem><simpara>
		   Thin client access to a website (<xref linkend="logins:firefox"/>)
		 </simpara></listitem>
	   </itemizedlist>
	</para>

	<para>
	  Once the wizard is finished, the UCC clients now need to be registered in the &ucsUMC;. This
	  is described in <xref linkend="umc:manageucc"/>.
	</para>

  </section>

  <section id="umc:manageucc">
	 <title>Managing UCC systems in the &ucsUMC;</title>

	 <para>
	   UCC systems are registered and administrated with the system role <emphasis>Univention
	   Corporate Client</emphasis> in the computer management module of the &ucsUMC;.
	   The UCC setup wizard automatically creates three computer containers for thin clients
	   (<uri>cn=computers, cn=ucc-thinclients</uri>), desktop systems
	   (<uri>cn=computers, cn=ucc-desktops</uri>). These should be selected in the
	   <guimenu>Container</guimenu> input field depending on the type of the UCC client.
	 </para>

	 <para>
	   In the default setting, the dialogue window for creating a UCC system only shows the most
	   important input fields. Clicking on <guimenu>Advanced</guimenu> shows all the options. This
	   is only necessary in exceptional cases.
	 </para>

	 <para>
	   The following settings must be configured for every UCC client as a minimum:

	   <itemizedlist>
		 <listitem><simpara>
		   The <guimenu>Hostname</guimenu> of the client (composed of lowercase and uppercase
		 letters, numbers, hyphens and underscores).
		 </simpara></listitem>

		 <listitem><simpara>
		   The <emphasis>MAC address</emphasis> of the client in the notation <systemitem class="etheraddress">XX:XX:XX:XX:XX:XX</systemitem>. It
		   is required for DHCP.
		 </simpara></listitem>

		 <listitem><simpara>
		   A <guimenu>Network</guimenu> needs to be selected: generally the network configured in the UCC
		   Setup wizard. The <guimenu>IP address</guimenu> is suggested automatically and can be
		   adjusted if necessary.
		 </simpara></listitem>
	   </itemizedlist>
	 </para>

	 <para>
	   Each UCC client must be registered in the DNS and DHCP. The network object assigns these
	   entries automatically. If a UCC client is created without a network object (which is only
	   needed in exceptional cases), it is important to ensure that the entries for the
	   <guimenu>Forward zone for DNS entry</guimenu>, <guimenu>Reverse zone for DNS entry</guimenu>
	   and <guimenu>DHCP service</guimenu> are configured.
	 </para>

	 <para>
	   The assigned name server is preconfigured automatically. If it is necessary to adjust the
	   assigned server, the <guimenu>DHCP DNS</guimenu> <emphasis>default-settings</emphasis> policy
	   must be edited.
	 </para>

	 <para>
	   Clicking on <guimenu>Next</guimenu> configures the assigned UCC image and the boot
	   version. The boot versions are documented in <xref linkend="rollout:imagerollout"/>.
	 </para>

	 <para>
		 UCC clients save their currently installed image in the UCS <literal>LDAP</literal>.
		 This makes it possible to search for UCC clients with outdated images and configure them
		 to update their image on the next boot. In the <guimenu>Computers</guimenu> module extended search options,
		 one can search for the object <guimenu>Type</guimenu> <literal>Univention Corporate Client</literal>,
		 and the property <literal>image name</literal>. Multiple objects can then be edited simultaneously
		 to update their boot settings.
	 </para>
  </section>

  <section id="umc:nagios">
	<title>Monitoring UCC systems with Nagios</title>

	<para>
	  &ucsUCS; integrates Nagios for the monitoring of systems and services. UCC systems can also be
	  integrated in the Nagios monitoring. To this end, the <guimenu>Nagios support</guimenu> option
	  must be enabled under <guimenu>Options</guimenu> in the &ucsUMC; for the systems to be
	  monitored on the computer object. More information on Nagios can be found in the UCS manual <biblioref
	  linkend="ucs-manual-nagios"/>.

	</para>

	<para>
	  In the default setting, the NRPE service is not installed on UCC systems. That means that only
	  remote Nagios checks can be applied.
	</para>

  </section>

</chapter>
