<chapter id="umc:chapter">
  <title>Management of UCC systems in the &ucsUMC;</title>

  <section id="umc:initialsetup">
	<title>Initial setting up of a UCC environment</title>
	<para>
	  A setup wizard is provided for the initial configuration of a UCC environment. This guides you
	  through the basic setting up of a UCC environment with thin clients or desktop
	  clients. Different standard policies are created and configured. The setup wizard is suitable
	  for small to medium-sized environments. The policies can also be manually configured in the
	  &ucsUMC; for more complex requirements in which different policies are to be used for
	  different containers of the LDAP directory or multiple DHCP subnets are to be operated. The
	  policies required for each option is listed in the respective chapters.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The setup wizard is started via the &ucsUMC; module <guimenu>UCC Setup</guimenu>. In the main
	  menu, you can firstly select whether to set up thin clients and/or desktop systems. The UCC
	  image(s) is/are then downloaded depending on the selection.
	</para>

	<para>
	  UCS offers you the possibility of centrally managing the IP addresses and DNS/DHCP settings of
	  a network in a network object in the LDAP. This can considerably facilitates the management of
	  IP addresses: When creating a UCC client the next free IP address of the network is selected
	  automatically. Also, DNS and DHCP settings are configured automatically.
	</para>

	<para>
	  It is now possible to select an existing network object in the <guimenu>Network
	  configuration</guimenu> dialogue or create a new one. During the installation of an UCS
	  system, a network object with the name <emphasis>default</emphasis> is created as standard.
	  It uses the network of the &ucsMaster;. If only a certain IP segment is to be used for the UCC
	  systems, a new network object can be created with the <guimenu>Specify a new IP
	  segment</guimenu> dialogue. For example, if the IP addresses 192.168.100.100 to
	  192.168.100.200 are used for UCC systems, <emphasis>192.168.100.0</emphasis> must be entered
	  as the <guimenu>Network address</guimenu>, <emphasis>24</emphasis> as the
	  <guimenu>Netmask</guimenu> and <emphasis>192.168.100.100</emphasis> /
	  <emphasis>192.168.100.200</emphasis> entered as the <guimenu>First IP address / Last IP
	  address</guimenu>.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The network configuration of UCC clients is managed through DHCP in nearly all cases (the only
	  exception are UCC terminal servers). 
	  <!-- Der Wizard prüft, ob ein Default Gateway über DHCP -->
	  <!-- zugewiesen wird. Ist das nicht der Fall, wird ein Dialog angezeigt, in dem das Gateway -->
	  <!-- konfiguriert werden kann. -->
	  In the default setting, fixed IP addresses are assigned and only to
	  clients registered in the LDAP.
	</para>
	
  </section>

  <section id="umc:manageucc">
	 <title>Managing UCC systems in the &ucsUMC;</title>

	 <para>
	   UCC systems are registered and administrated with the system role <emphasis>Univention
	   Corporate Client</emphasis> in the computer management module of the &ucsUMC;. 
	   The UCC setup wizard automatically creates two computer containers for thin clients
	   (<emphasis>cn=computers, cn=ucc-thinclients</emphasis>) and desktop systems
	   (<emphasis>cn=computers, cn=ucc-desktops</emphasis>). These should be selected in the
	   <guimenu>Container</guimenu> input field depending on the type of the UCC client.
	 </para>

	 <!-- <para> -->
	 <!--   In der Grundeinstellung zeigt der Dialog zum Anlegen eines UCC-Systems nur die wichtigsten -->
	 <!--   Eingabefelder an. Mit einem Klick auf <guimenu>Advanced</guimenu> werden alle Optionen -->
	 <!--   angezeigt. Dies ist aber nur in Ausnahmefällen nötig. -->
	 <!-- </para> -->

	 <para>
	   The following settings must be configured for every UCC client as a minimum:

	   <itemizedlist>
		 <listitem><simpara>
		   The <guiname>Hostname</guiname> of the client (composed of lowercase and uppercase
		 letters, numbers, hyphens and underscores).
		 </simpara></listitem>

		 <listitem><simpara>
		   The <emphasis>MAC address</emphasis> of the client in the notation XX:XX:XX:XX:XX:XX. It
		   is required for DHCP.
		 </simpara></listitem>
		 
		 <!-- <listitem><simpara> -->
		 <!--   Ein <guimenu>Network</guimenu> muss ausgewählt werden, in der Regel das Netzwerk, das im -->
		 <!--   UCC Setup Wizard angelegt werden. Die <guimenu>IP address</guimenu> wird automatisch -->
		 <!--   vorgeschlagen und kann ggf. angepasst werden. -->
		 <!-- </simpara></listitem> -->
	   </itemizedlist>
	 </para>

	 <!-- <para> -->
	 <!--   Jeder UCC-Client muss im DNS und DHCP registriert sein. Das Netzwerk-Objekt weist diese -->
	 <!--   Einträge automatisch zu. Wird ein UCC-Client ohne Netzwerk-Objekt angelegt (was nur in -->
	 <!--   Ausnahmefällen sinnvoll ist), muss darauf geachtet werden, das Einträge für die <guimenu>Forward zone for -->
	 <!--   DNS entry</guimenu>, <guimenu>Reverse zone for DNS entry</guimenu> und <guimenu>DHCP -->
	 <!--   service</guimenu> konfiguriert sind. -->
	 <!-- </para> -->

	 <!-- <para> -->
	 <!--   Der zugewiesene Nameserver ist automatisch vorkonfiguriert. Wenn der zugewiesene Server -->
	 <!--   angepasst werden soll muss dazu die <emphasis>default-settings</emphasis>-Richtlinie von Typ -->
	 <!--   <guimenu>DHCP DNS</guimenu> editiert werden. -->
	 <!-- </para> -->

	 <!-- <para> -->
	 <!--   Ein Klick auf <guimenu>Next</guimenu> führt zur Konfiguration des zugewiesenen UCC-Images und -->
	 <!--   der Boot-Variante. Die Boot-Varianten sind in <xref linkend="rollout:imagerollout"/> -->
	 <!--   dokumentiert. -->
	 <!-- </para> -->

  </section>

</chapter>