<chapter id="logins:chapter">
  <title>User logins</title>
  <section id="logins:lightdm">
	<title>User logins on LightDM</title>

	<section id="logins:sessions">
	  <title>Session selection</title>
	  <para>
		UCC uses LightDM as its login manager. When the UCC client is started, a login mask is
		shown. The user can choose between different session types using the
		<guimenu>Session</guimenu> menu.
	  </para>

	  <para>
		If the UCC client is not yet joined or in live boots, an automatic login is performed with a
		temporary guest user. Such an automatic login can also be configured for joined systems, see
		<xref linkend="logins:autologin"/>
	  </para>

	  <figure><title>User login at LightDM</title>
	  <graphic scalefit="1" width="80%" fileref="illustrations/ucc-lightdm.png"/>
	  </figure>

	  <para>
		If a password has expired or a user is scheduled for a password change the next time she
		logs in, the password change is performed in the scope of the login. Password changes are
		currently not possible when using the RDP session script, this will be fixed in a future
		release.
	  </para>

	  <para>
		It must be noted that although the &ucsUMC; permits the creation of users with a space in
		their user name - as these user names are legitimate in Active Directory domains - it is not
		possible to logon to UCC clients with these user names.
	  </para>

	  <para>
		The last chosen user session is cached per user.
	  </para>

	  <figure><title>Session selection at LightDM</title>
	  <graphic scalefit="1" width="40%" fileref="illustrations/ucc-session-selection.png"/>
	  </figure>

	  <para>
		The following session scripts are supported:
		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem><simpara>
			Univention Corporate Client based on KDE (on a local system and to a XRDP terminal server)
			(<xref linkend="terminalservices:xrdp"/>, <xref linkend="desktop:chapter"/>)
		  </simpara></listitem>

		  <listitem><simpara>
			Citrix XenApp (<xref linkend="terminalservices:citrix"/>)
		  </simpara></listitem>

		  <listitem><simpara>
			Microsoft Windows Terminal Server (<xref linkend="terminalservices:rdp"/>)
		  </simpara></listitem>

		  <listitem><simpara>
			Firefox (with direct login to a configured website) (<xref linkend="logins:firefox"/>)
		  </simpara></listitem>

		  <listitem><simpara>
			LXDE (Lightweight X11 Desktop Environment) (<xref linkend="desktop:chapter"/>)
		  </simpara></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	  </para>
	</section>

	<section id="logins:sessiondefault">
	  <title>Configuration of a default session for a user's first login</title>
	  <para>
		To configure the default session that is set for a user's first login on a client, the
		&ucsUCRV; <envar>lightdm/sessiondefault</envar> must contain the name of one of the session
		scripts in <filename>/usr/share/xsessions</filename>. For subsequent logins on a client the
		last chosen session is cached on a per user basis.
		<!-- Wurde die UCC-Umgebung über den UCC setup wizard konfiguriert (siehe (<xref -->
		<!-- linkend="umc:initialsetup"/>), ist die Einstellung schon vorkonfiguriert. -->
	  </para>
	</section>

	<section id="logins:autologin">
	  <title>Configuration of an automatic login and session selection</title>
	  <para>
		Instead of an interactive login, it is also possible to configure an automatic login. This
		is useful for a UCC client which is only used for access to terminal services or to a
		website (e.g., for kiosk systems).
	  </para>

	  <para>
		This is done by setting the &ucsUCRV; <envar>lightdm/autologin</envar> to
		<emphasis>yes</emphasis> and <envar>lightdm/autologin/session</envar> to a session
		script. The session scripts can be found in the <filename>/usr/share/xsessions</filename>
		directory, in other words, <emphasis>firefox</emphasis> for example.
	  </para>

	  <para>
		By default a temporary guest user is used for the automatic login. Alternatively, the
		&ucsUCRV; <envar>lightdm/autologin/user</envar> allows the configuration of the user under
		which the automatic login should occur. 
	  </para>

	  <para>
		If an automatic login is configured, the LightDM login dialogue is no longer shown. The session can
		alternatively also be specified in the user management of the &ucsUMC;. This is performed in
		the <guimenu>Force this session for user logins</guimenu> input field in the <emphasis>UCC
		user session</emphasis> policy: Independently of the selection of the session script during
		the LightDM user login, the login is always performed with the predefined session. The
		sessions available in the policy can be extended, see <xref linkend="logins:sessionobjects"/>.
	  </para>
	</section>

	<section id="logins:sessionscripts">
	  <title>Session scripts</title>
	  <para>
		Scripts can be run at different times during session setup and when exiting the session. All
		executable scripts in the following directories are run alphabetically with root
		rights:

		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem><simpara>
			<filename>/etc/lightdm/session-setup</filename>: Is run before the session script is
			executed.
		  </simpara></listitem>

		  <listitem><simpara>
			<filename>/etc/lightdm/session-cleanup</filename>: Is run after the session script is
			exited.
		  </simpara></listitem>

		  <listitem><simpara>
			<filename>/etc/lightdm/display-setup</filename>: Is run if a greeter session is run.
		  </simpara></listitem>

		  <listitem><simpara>
			<filename>/etc/lightdm/greeter-setup</filename>: Is run if a greeter session is started.
		  </simpara></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	  </para>
	</section>

	<section id="logins:environmentvars">
	  <title>Configuration of environment variables and execution of scripts during user login</title>
	  <para>
		A <guimenu>UCC desktop settings</guimenu> user policy can be used to configure environment
		variables in the user session. All the variables set with the <guimenu>Variable</guimenu>
		and <guimenu>Value</guimenu> options are then set in the user session
		scripts.
	  </para>

	  <para>
		The scripts set via the <guimenu>Desktop logon scripts</guimenu> and <guimenu>Desktop
		logout scripts</guimenu> settings are run before and after the user login with the rights of
		the accessing user. They must be specified as absolute file names and must not contain any spaces. Also,
		the scripts must be executable.
	  </para>

	</section>
  </section>

  <section id="logins:localcaching">
	<title>Local caching of user and group information</title>
	<para>
	  UCC systems store user and group information in local files integrated via an NSS module. In
	  combination with caching of the login credentials (see <xref linkend="logins:pwcaching"/>),
	  this allows operation of UCC clients without a connection to an LDAP server of the UCS domain.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The user and group information is extracted via a listener module
	  (<filename>ucc-nss-passwd.py</filename>) on the UCS-based UCC servers into a
	  <filename>passwd</filename> and a <filename>group</filename> file.
	</para>

	<para>
	  These files are read from UCC systems via an NSS module (<package>libnss-extrausers</package>). The user and
	  group data are downloaded in two ways:

	  <itemizedlist>
		<listitem><simpara>
		  The current files are downloaded when the UCC client is started.
		</simpara></listitem>

		<listitem><simpara>
		  If the user is not yet present on the UCC system, the download is also initiated during
		login via the PAM stack.
		</simpara></listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</para>

	<para>
	  If the &ucsUCRV; <envar>ucc/nss/update/force</envar> is set to <emphasis>true</emphasis>, the
	  user and group information is obtained during every login.
	</para>

	<para>
	  As standard, all of the users in the domain are always copied to the client. For special cases
	  - such as notebooks, on which only a few users should be present - the &ucsUCRV;
	  <envar>ucc/nss/update/hostspecific</envar> should be set to <emphasis>true</emphasis>. In this
	  case, the download script for the user data on the UCS server searches for the
	  <filename>/var/cache/ucc/HOSTNAME.passwd</filename> and
	  <filename>/var/cache/ucc/HOSTNAME.group</filename> files in which system-specific user data
	  can be stored.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="logins:pwcaching">
	<title>Logins to offline UCC systems / password credentials caching</title>
	<para>
	  Kerberos authentication is performed on UCC systems with a network connection.
	</para>

	<para>
	  In addition, successful login attempts are cached via the PAM module <package>pam_ccreds</package>, i.e., if a
	  user has successfully logged in once with an active network connection, she can also continue
	  to log in with this password when working offline.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="logins:firefox">
	<title>Firefox session script</title>
	<para>
	  The Firefox session script starts a Firefox web browser in a fullscreen session. It can be
	  used, for example, to access an intranet page directly from thin clients or to configure a
	  groupware web client.
	</para>

	<para>
	  For setting up the Firefox access to a website, the <guimenu>UCC Setup</guimenu> wizard must
	  be opened in the &ucsUMC;. The <guimenu>Configure direct web browser access to a preconfigured
	  web site</guimenu> option must be selected under <guimenu>Thin client configuration</guimenu>
	  in the <guimenu>Configuration of terminal services</guimenu> submenu.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The website to be accessed should be entered in the <guimenu>Automatically connect to this web
	  site</guimenu> input field. If the wizard is not used, the &ucsUCRV;
	  <envar>firefox/startsite</envar> must be configured.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="logins:sessionobjects">
	<title>Registration of sessions in the Univention Management Console</title>
	<para>
	  Sessions are registered in the &ucsUMC;. New sessions can be
	  created by selecting the UMC module <guimenu>LDAP
	  directory</guimenu> and adding a <guimenu>UCC session
	  script</guimenu> object below <emphasis>cn=univention,cn=UCC,dc=Session</emphasis>.
	</para>
  </section>

</chapter>
